<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rejoynder to Mr. Daniel Williams his reply to the first part of Neomianism [sic] unmaskt wherein his defence is examined, and his arguments answered : whereby he endeavours to prove the Gospel to be a new law with sanction, and the contrary is proved / by Isaac Chauncy.</title>
            <author>Chauncy, Isaac, 1632-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12952506</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12952506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32773)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 733:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rejoynder to Mr. Daniel Williams his reply to the first part of Neomianism [sic] unmaskt wherein his defence is examined, and his arguments answered : whereby he endeavours to prove the Gospel to be a new law with sanction, and the contrary is proved / by Isaac Chauncy.</title>
                  <author>Chauncy, Isaac, 1632-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Barnard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716. --  Defence of Gospel truth.</term>
               <term>Neonomianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95981:1"/>
            <p>A REJOYNDER TO Mr. <hi>DANIEL WILLIAMS</hi> HIS REPLY To the Firſt Part of <hi>Neomianiſm Vnmaſkt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN His Defence is Examined, and his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Anſwered; whereby he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prove the Goſpel to be a New Law with Sanction: And the contrary is proved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ISAAC CHA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCY,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Barnard,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95981:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95981:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A REJOYNDER TO Mr. <hi>Daniel Williams</hi> his REPLY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU ſay you are miſrepreſented, in my ſaying, You hold the Vacating or Abrogating the Old Law.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> This is no falſe Charge or Miſrepreſentation, for if the Sanction be changed, as you expreſsly ſay, both in the former Book and in this, the Law is vacated, it ceaſeth to be <hi>Norma Judicii,</hi> and what Paſſage you refer to in p. 198. of your former Book, relieves you not. P. 198. where you ſay, The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Action of the holieſt Saint needs forgiveneſs: For upon your Hypotheſis, there is general Pardon purchaſed conditionally, which Faith and ſincere Holineſs entitleth us to. The old Law itſelf is laid aſide, as that which will never trouble the Believer; Chriſt hath ſatisfied that for him, but it is the new Law which the Believer muſt be tryed by; which is the Goſpel Law, and hath another Sanction to the preceptive part of the Law which the Covenant of Works had preſcribed. P. 6. This new Law, you ſay, fixeth new Terms, <hi>viz.</hi> True Repentance and Faith unfeigned, to be the Terms of Pardon; which Terms, you ſay, the Covenant of Works admitteth not, ſo that the Terms or Conditions being changed, the Sanction is changed: What remains then but a new Law, the righteouſneſs of which muſt be our juſtifying Righteouſneſs, for there's no Juſtification by any Law without fulfilling it, by performance of that very Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs by our ſelves, or another, which that Law requires. And tho' you ſay, we are bound to the Duties of the Moral Law, yet you ſay, the uſe of Faith and Holineſs, in reſpect of the Benefits, is not from their conformity to the Precept [ſo that Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Precept of the old Law hath nothing to do as Righteouſneſs in the new Law] but their Conformity to the Rule of the Promiſe, which can be no other than the Rule of the new Law. Hence it is manifeſt, That with you this new Law is diſtinct, both in Precept and Sanction; therefore it's out a doors. Laſtly, none can deny, But that how good ſoever the Precept of a Law is, if the ſanction be vacated or changed, ſo that it ceaſeth to be <hi>Norma Judicii,</hi> it ceaſeth to be a Law; and where a Law ceaſeth to be <hi>Norma Judicii,</hi> there's no tryal to be made thereby of Men's Actions, no Judicial Proceedings thereby, nor Juſtification or Condemnation by it; whatever we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95981:3"/> are, in reſpect of another Law, our Righteouſneſs muſt be judged of and tryed by the Law in Force; and this is your plain Judgment. See p. 131. you ſay, <q>If Men have nothing to do for Salvation, then Chriſt hath no Rule to judge them who lived under the Goſpel.</q> So that Men under the Goſpel are judged by a Rule of doing, which is your Rule of the Promiſe. And again, <hi>ibid.</hi> 
               <q>Conſider the deſcription of the laſt Day, and you'l find God Saves and Damns with reſpect to Mens Neglects and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Goſpel.</q> You ſay, it's true, the Sanction of the Law of Works is removed, p. 135. Your granting, That we deſerve Wrath, in reſpect of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, and that the Law is a Rule of Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is nothing, for 'tis not meer ſatisfying that Law will ſave us, or the Righteouſneſs thereof, but a Compliance with, and obedience to a new Law. You ſay, <hi>The Law cannot hinder our Relief by Chriſt, from the Sentence:</hi> Chriſt ſtands between us and that Law, that we may be ſaved by another. Forgiveneſs, you ſay, is not by ſinleſs Obedience [we ſay, it is by Chriſt's, which s ſinleſs Obedience] but it is by our imperfect Obedience that muſt follow. You ſay alſo in this Reply, p. 23. <q>Were not the Goſpel to be a Rule of Judgment <hi>(norma Judicii,)</hi> I cannot ſee how that can be a Judgment Day, it muſt be only an Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Day; for by the Law of <hi>Adam</hi> no Believer could be acquitted; that Law muſt be altered by the Law-giver, to admit Satisfaction (which is a ſtrange Expreſſion, as if Chriſt could not ſatisfy <hi>Adam</hi>'s Law, without altering it, the Law muſt be vacated if Chriſt ſatisfied and fulfilled it, <hi>cujus contrarium verum eſt</hi>) "and it is by the Goſpel only he hath enacted the way how this Satisfaction ſhall be applyed:</q> And that way enacted is your new Law that comes in the room and ſtead of the old Law, vacated. Therefore, I beſeech you, conſider your own Reputation more than to ſay, I miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent you, in ſaying, You hold that which your Words ſhew, your Scheme muſt contain, and you know in your Conſcience is your Principle.</p>
            <p>Again, you charge me for miſrepreſenting you, whenas you ſay; <q>Chriſt's Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are the Foundation of our Pardon; that our Sins are forgiven for Chriſt's Sufferings.</q> By my ſaying, Your <hi>Fundamentally</hi> is only a remote cauſality <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> by ſomething elſe beſides them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You know, whatever you ſay, to palliate it, that you mean Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is our legal Righteouſneſs; but our Faith and Obedience, our evangelical Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which you own under the Name of a ſubordinate Righteouſneſs, and is not the Inference of <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> p. 20. Very natural, when you ſay, For the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt our Sins are forgiven, and explain it thus: Without them Sin cannot be forgiven. How can a <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non</hi> be more plainly expreſſed; as thus, The going out of my Door is the <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> of my going into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> How ſo? without going out of my Houſe (which is in another Street,) I cannot go into <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <q>It's ſtrange that any one ſhould infer, That you deny the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, to be the ſole meritorious or material Cauſe of our Pardon, which in Judicial Acts are the ſame.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Rej.</label>All this may be, and your contrary Senſe to us ſtill the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It's one thing to be a meritorious cauſe of Pardon, and another thing to be our very ſole juſtifying Righteouſneſs. I can ſay Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is the ſole meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Cauſe of Sanctification, for which we are ſanctified, as well as for which we are forgiven; and yet we are ſanctified by the Spirit: and ſo for which we are adopted. Hence you will ſay, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is the meritorious Cauſe for which we are pardoned and juſtified by the Goſpel-law, the Condition whereof you make Meetneſs (what is required of Sinners is only a meetneſs to receive the Effects) this <hi>Meetneſs</hi> is the Evangelical Righteouſneſs; this is the Condition we ſhall be tryed by at the laſt Day, and this is the Law Condition upon which we receive the effects of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs; not the righteouſneſs itſelf neither: And is not this Meetneſs a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Cauſe in the Goſpel Law of our receiving theſe Effects? Why then hath it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame Place in reſpect of the new Law as Chriſt's Righteouſneſs hath, in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95981:3"/> repect of the old Law, ſo that there muſt be at leaſt two Righteouſneſſes requiſite to our compleat Juſtification, one Righteouſneſs to anſwer the Old Law, and another to anſwer the New? And indeed here Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is made by you moſt properly the ſubordinate Righteouſneſs, becauſe it is <hi>in ordine ad,</hi> it's only in order to an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Righteouſneſs. In the moſt favoura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Senſe, you make the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to merit <hi>ex condigno,</hi> and Evang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lical to merit <hi>ex congruo,</hi> for all Law Meetneſs is meriting, either in reſpect of the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative or minatory part of the Law. All that you ſay over and over helps not, nor covers you from thoſe that know your Dialect; nor your ſaying, That Chriſt is the foundation of your Plea: I may found a Plea or Argument upon a thing that is not my Plea, or at leaſt my chief Plea, and how do you found it? Why, for the ſake of Chriſt, accepted againſt excluding bars, you ſay; whereby you have Permiſſion now to come in with your Evangelical Righteouſneſs. You ſpeak here juſt as in your other Book, to this Point, and I underſtand you ſtill as I did then, and you know you mean as I have repreſented your Meaning, but you would not have the People under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what you mean; and therefore you throw in an abundance of Expreſſions, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to hide your Opinion, but inſtead thereof they lay it open. What is more plain than this? <hi>Repl.</hi> p. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The Terms of the Goſpel by the Promiſe do make us <hi>capable</hi> of being juſtified and ſaved for the Merits of Chriſt.</q> Now here's your true ſenſe of being forgiven for the Merits of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> when we are made capable by the <hi>righteous Meetneſs</hi> of another Law, we ſhall be abſolved in the old Law ſenſe, by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt. And mark that all along, its forgiveneſs only comes from Chriſt's Merits; there's no poſitive righteouſneſs of Chriſt, in active Obedience, is reckoned to us; this poſitive righteouſneſs whereby we ſtand juſt in the Eye of the Law, in your ſenſe lies wholy in Conformity to the Rule of that Promiſe, which is the new Law righteouſneſs: And you uſe the word Merits ſtill, in the way of procuration, not ſatisfaction. You ſay we are juſtified only by Chriſt's Merits, as the ſole procuring cauſe or righteouſneſs for which we are juſtified [to which you ſhould add, that the Reader might take your full ſenſe] by the righteouſneſs of the Goſpel Law.</p>
            <p>That which you call the fifth Miſrepreſentation, and is your fourth, I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of, but that my Inferences are truly drawn, according to your natural ſenſe and meaning of what your Expreſſions and what your Principles muſt bear, 1. That you make the great end and uſe of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to ſecure us from the old Law, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> calls it our legal Righteouſneſs: and therefore our Juſtification is not an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate effect of that Righteouſneſs, but of our evangelical Righteouſneſs. 2. That he merited only that we might Merit, <hi>i. e.</hi> that he procured our Juſtification by evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Righteouſneſs; you will not call it Merit; call it what you will, <hi>its a Law of Meetneſs;</hi> and a Law meetneſs I think, gives a claim and challenge of Pardon; and if we ſhould pray in your Dialect, we ſhould pray thus, <hi>Lord, I am meet to be pardoned for the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> 3. That you make Faith and Repentance the meritorious cauſe of Pardon and Glory by the new Law, and that's true, for all conformity to, and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the conditional Preceptive part of a Law gives right, a legal right to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneration, and the benefit becomes a reward of Debt; and if ſo, the meetneſs is a Merit, <hi>ex Pacto.</hi> All theſe, <hi>tho</hi> you ſay, you diſown, <hi>yet</hi> in what you declare, you ſay but what you ſaid before, and from whence the ſame Conſequences will follow, <hi>viz.</hi> That God requires a meetneſs in a Sinner for Juſtification, and that this meetneſs is a federal condition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You ſay, Chriſt ſatisfied Juſtice and merited Pardon and Glory, <hi>i. e.</hi> he ſatisfied Juſtice in reſpect of the old Law, and merited Pardon and Glory, to be beſtowed as Rewards of Obedience to another Law: And that</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sinner thus partaking of them, is as Fruits of his Death; and this is all done for his ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95981:4"/>3. You ſay, God in Chriſt hath declared a way and order how he will diſpenſe his Benefits; this way is by another Law, in which he acts in a way of diſtribution of Juſtice, upon performance of Law conditions, <hi>p.</hi> 4. And therefore you ſay, Goſpel conditions have no other uſe to our Intereſt in theſe Benefits, than a complyance with this ſtated Rule of the diſtribution of Pardon and Glory, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Adam</hi>'s obedience had no other uſe, than a compliance with the ſtated Rule of Gods diſtribution of Life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and Pardon and Glory is no other than Life promiſed. So that you make your Law to be every whit the ſame <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> with a Covenant or Law of Works; the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion works out the reward of Debt; but this is all the difference, that Man fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firſt Covenant of Works by Creation, but under the ſecond by Redemption; he was redeemed from the Curſe of the old Law that he might be juſtified by another Law Covenant; and this is your plain meaning, as you ſay: And theſe things you do but ſay over and over again in this Book, as in the former. And what doth this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Grant of theſe Effects import, but that we ſhould have Juſtification, Adoption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the performance of obedience to another Law? Which is as much as to ſay, Chriſt purchaſed another Law, and Obedience to it muſt let us into Pardon by Chriſt. This purchaſing conditional Grants and Propoſitions, is a new ſort of Divinity, ſuiting the higheſt degree of Arminian Doctrin, and will ſtrike at the nature of abſolute Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which gives ground of ſuſpecting you alſo in that Point, as well as what you ſay of the ſavability of the none Elect; tho' I acknowledge you often aſſert abſolute Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but how well that Principle will comport with indefinite Redemption, upon a conditional Grant, let the rational judge. You go on again, and ſay, as from <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Pag.</hi> 84. of your firſt Book. <q>When Sinners are pardoned, the whole meritorious cauſe of that Pardon, is that attonement; and what is required of Sinners, is only a meetneſs to receive the Effects.</q> You need quote no more, to give us an account of what you mean in theſe things; if the Reader deſires to be further confirmed in the truth of my repreſentation of your Principles, let him read <hi>pag.</hi> 4, 5. of your Reply.</p>
            <p>You quote Paſſages in <hi>p.</hi> 30, 31. of my Book (for the firſt Head) from whence you ſay, <q>I endeavour to render you one, that thinks Faith or other Graces did merit the pardon of our Sins; which you ſay, is contrary to your declared Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Rep.</label> I grant you deny Merit; and I profeſs, Sir, I would not willingly wrong you by any falſe Imputation; but this I tell you, it ſignifies not much to deny a Name to a thing whoſe Nature requires that Name if it be named aright; a federal condition per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, doth bring a Man into the claim of the benefits promiſed as Debt, your own word gives the performance of the condition the <hi>meritum ex congruo,</hi> merit of meetneſs; and you making this meetneſs federal, I know not how it can be avoided but it will be Merit.</p>
            <p>You quote Proofs, that you do not call this meetneſs Merit, but you call Chriſt's Righteouſneſs the Merit, as this; there is a <hi>Righteouſneſs for which a Man is juſtified, and that is only Chriſts:</hi> But you'l ſay, there is a Righteouſneſs of meetneſs upon which a Man is juſtified for Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> the qualifing condition of the Perſon whom this Mercy is promiſed to, he muſt have a Conformity to the Rule of the Promiſe; and its by this we are juſtified for the righteouſneſs of Chriſt. To what purpoſe is it to deny Repentance and Faith, to be meriting Righteouſneſs; when according to your Scheme, it can be denied in no other ſenſe than in reſpect of the Covenant of Works? The ſatisfaction of the breach whereof, you acknowledge to lie in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt conditionally, <hi>i. e.</hi> for all that ſhall conform to the Rule of the Promiſe, which Rule is the preceptive part of the new Law; which Conformity you call, with others, ſubordinate Righteouſneſs, intituling us to another Righteouſneſs; it's this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you ſay, we ſhall be judged by at the laſt day. Now Sir, I ſay, that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which Believers ſhall be acquitted by in the day of Judgment, that is the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that they were juſtified by, and the Righteouſneſs of that Law which they ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95981:4"/> be judged by. Let us but a little conſider how near this ſubordinate Righteouſneſs comes to the Papiſt's Notion of Merit, and if their Merit be not as ſmall a thing as your meetneſs and new Law conditions of Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Hear what S. <hi>de Clara</hi> our Countryman tells us.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Meritum eſt Actio libera acceptata ad aliquod premium.</p>
               <p>Meritum de congruo eſt Actio libera ex congruitate quâdam acceptata ad premium.</p>
               <p>Meritum de condigno, eſt Actio libera ab Homine in gratiâ elicita qui ex Juſtitia acceptatur ad premium.</p>
               <p>Merit is a free Action, accepted to ſome Reward.</p>
               <p>Merit of meetneſs is a free Action, which by reaſon of ſome congruity or fitneſs is accepted to a Reward.</p>
               <p>Merit of worthineſs is a free Action of a Man performed in Grace, which from Juſtice is accepted to a Reward.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Now the Queſtion is, 1. Whether that perſonal Qualification, which you require of <hi>meetneſs</hi> for Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, be not exactly the Papiſts Merit of <hi>Congruity?</hi> Upon which is their firſt Juſtification. 2. And the ſincere imperfect preſevering Obedience be not their <hi>Meritum ex condigno,</hi> or of Worthineſs? Which is their ſecond Juſtification.</p>
            <p>See the firſt Juſtific. the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Decr. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beginning of Juſtification of the Adult, proceedeth from preventing Grace which inviteth to diſpoſe themſelves, conſenting and co-operating with it freely,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The manner of this Preparation is, to believe willingly the divine Revelations and Promiſes, and knowing ones ſelf to be a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to turn from the fear of God's Juſtice to his Mercy, to hope for Pardon, and to begin to love him, hate Sin, purpoſe to be baptized,</hi> &amp;c. Decr. 7. <hi>Juſtification followeth this Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Decr. 8. <hi>When a Man is juſtified by Faith, and gratis, it ought to be underſtood, becauſe Faith is the beginning, and the things that preceed Juſtification, are not meritorious of Grace,</hi> And in another F. <hi>they condemn thoſe that ſay, A Man may be juſtified without Grace, by the ſtrength of Human Nature, and the Doctrine of the Law.</hi> What is it that you ſay of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Meetneſs, which they will not ſay in behalf of your <hi>congruity?</hi> And <hi>Scotus</hi> tells us, That an act is not meritorious preciſely, becauſe it comes from Grace, but becauſe it is accepted of God, as worthy of eternal Life, as you ſay it's the Promiſe made to that meetneſs gives the right.</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>meritum de congruo,</hi> merit of meetneſs, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> diſputes, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 21. and concerning that <hi>de condigno, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de juſtificatione,</hi> the merit of Meetneſs he aſcribes to the Works of him that is to be juſtified, <hi>a partibus juſtificandi, i. e.</hi> that meetneſs for Juſtification by Repentance and Faith, previous to Juſtification and capacitating for it, or diſpoſing to it. The other, <hi>viz.</hi> Merit of Condignity, is aſcribed <hi>operibus juſtificati,</hi> to the evangelical ſincere Obedience of one juſtified by the firſt Juſtification, whereby he merits the ſecond Juſtification<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and though you will not own the Name Merit, yet in your Scheme, your firſt Juſtification by Meetneſs, or upon Meetneſs, and the ſecond upon perſevering imperfect Obedience, is the ſame Juſtifications that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> means, for the Jeſuite ſaith thus, The perfection of our Righteouſneſs and Juſtification is not from Faith but from Works, for Faith doth but begin Juſtification, and after it hath aſſumed to itſelf Hope and Charity, it doth perfect it. <hi>Bellar. de Juſtif. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20. And again he ſaith, <hi>de merit.</hi> 
               <q>Good Works merit without all doubt, yet not by any intrinſick Vertue and Worth in them, but by vertue of God's Promiſe, and is not this as much as you ſay again and again, It is the Promiſe that gives Right to Benefits upon our Conformity to the Rule of the Promiſe, p. 104.</q> And <hi>Calvin, inſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ſ.</hi> 12. <q>They are forced to deny the intrinſick worthineſs of Works, and grant the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95981:5"/> of Works is always imperfect, while we live here, and wants forgiveneſs whereby our Failure in Works may be made up.</q> He makes it appear, That a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made with a Condition of a Work, brings this to paſs, that he who performs the Work is ſaid to have merited the thing promiſed, <hi>ex pacto,</hi> and may challenge his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as Debt in Law.</p>
            <p>It ſignifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not much whether you ſuppoſe the firſt Grace to be ſaving, or meer moral Endowment; the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> condemns them that ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Man may be <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied without Grace, by the ſtrength of Human Nature, and the doctrine of the Law:</hi> If you make the firſt Grace a qualifying meetneſs for Juſtification, in order thereto, it is the Papiſts Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee your ſheltering your ſelf under the abſoluteneſs of the firſt Grace, will not do: And, 1. Doth God give the firſt Grace abſolutely? then all other Graces conditionally, for the firſt Grace comes from the ſame foederal Condition that all doth. 2. The giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Grace is the giving eternal Life begun. 3. Either the firſt Grace is through Chriſt or not; but 'tis ſtrange to ſay, That Chriſt gives inherent Grace to one that's not united to him (but as his deſigned Head, as you phraſe it) and to one in a State of Condemnation: And ſhould make a change in his Nature before a change of State. 4. Then Sanctification, (if Faith be any part of it) muſt be before Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, contrary to the beſt Proteſtants, and what you have ſaid.</p>
            <p>Your 8th Exception is, That I ſay 'tis the Doctrine of Imputation that you banter; and you tell us what you ſay of it in your Book, where, when I come to the Places you quote here, you will ſee my Remarks on your Sayings: And ſo as to the ninth and tenth, it will be ſpoken to in its proper place: And as to the el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nth and twelfth, I am of the ſame Mind I was, I ſhall not ſpend Time in Vindication; and I leave the conſiderate Reader, who underſtands himſelf, whether I do not give a very fair account of your Opinion, whereof, by the Quotations of yours, out of your former Book, you give ſufficient Confirmation.</p>
            <p>As to the ſtating Queſtions in difference between us, you do it not fair: The firſt you ſay is, <hi>Preface</hi> 2. l. 1. Whether the elect are required to believe, that they may be juſtified? This, you ſay, I deny.</p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You ſhould have quoted the Place: I ſay there are Commands in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel unto Sinners, to believe and obey the Goſpel, that they may partake of Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, but not to perform it as a moral condition, that ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by they may be qualified for Juſtification, or made meet for it as you ſay.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>You ſay it is not whether the Goſpel be ſuch a Law, that the Acts of Obedience to it ſtand in the place of Works, ſo as for them we are ſaved; but whether the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel aſſure Salvation for Chriſt's Merits, to ſuch as obey it, and their active excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Salvation to ſuch as diſobey it?</q>
            </p>
            <p>This you ſay you affirm, and I deny; I'll tell you what I ſay: The Goſpel can't be a Law commanding Obedience as a federal condition of the Promiſe, but upon performance of it the Promiſe muſt be a reward of Debt; and if the Promiſe be Juſtification for the Merits of Chriſt, then its due as Debt upon the ſaid Obedience; and tho' you ſay, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication for the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, yet that Juſtification muſt be the reward of Obedience required in that Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>It is not whether we are juſtified by our Faith as an Act of ours, as if they [you mean Repentance too] as Works or Qualifications, were a Jot of that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs for which, or by which, we are juſtified: This I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Rep.</label>Who ſays you ſay its that Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, to which you annex your <hi>for, or by?</hi> but <hi>for</hi> and <hi>by</hi> this Righteouſneſs we come to be juſtified by our Faith and Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, the Duties required in another Law, which you tells us is the Goſpel Rule [<hi>i. e.</hi> your Law] <q>That a Man muſt be a penitent Believer whom God will juſtify, for the righteouſneſs of Chriſt: This you ſay you affirm and I deny, and that with good reaſon, that our Faith and Repentance muſt be previous, qualifying Duties to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95981:5"/> our Juſtification.</q> So that a Sinner muſt repent and believe in a ſtate of Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before he is juſtified: and its no more than this, that for Chriſt's Righteouſneſs which is our legal Righteouſneſs, we ſhall be juſtified by or according to our Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Your next Particular is the ſame; and I ſay as before, God doth not juſtifie us as a judicial Act for any Duty or Act, tho' wrought by the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You ſay, <q>It's not whether we are juſtified upon believing before any Works, which follow the firſt Act of ſaving Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> No, for the Papiſts own their firſt Juſtification to be ſo; but you ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <q>If Faith ſhould be ineffectual to Acts of ſincere Holineſs, and to prevent Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and utter Ungodlineſs, would we not be ſubject to condemnation by Goſpel Rule? This you ſay you affirm, and I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> Let us examin this then, and ſee what you affirm.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there's a poſſibility true juſtifying Faith may be ineffectual, and ſo there may be a falling away.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That till Faith hath brought forth ſincere perſevering Obedience we are not fully and certainly juſtified; we muſt be juſtified by the ſecond Juſtification, before we be ſecure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Apoſtacy and utter Ungodlineſs is prevented by a Goſpel Rule of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that we are made ſubject to; its a fine way to prevent Apoſtacy to lay us under a Rule of Condemnation, you mean a Sentence: For my part I can t ſee theſe things hang together, nor know what you mean by a Rule of Condemnation, but in the ſenſe of the Law working Wrath, which is quite contrary to the nature of a Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <q>You ſay and we ſay, That Holineſs and good Works are neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but that I deny they are indiſpenſable means of obtaining the Poſſeſſion of Salvation through Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> If I ſay they are neceſſary, it is enough, tho' I may not own them to be indiſpenſible means in your ſenſe, as a Law condition is an indiſpenſible means of the Reward; and if they be indiſpenſible means, the Thief upon the Croſs could not have been ſaved, and hundreds more, that I doubt not, but God ſaves in the like manner.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is not whether Juſtification, Adoption and Glorification be Acts of Gods free Grace, which I affirm.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label>But you ſaid otherwiſe, That forgiving, adopting and glorifying, and the conveyance of every promiſed Benefit, given on Gods Terms, are judicial Acts of God as a Rector, <hi>i. e.</hi> As you after ſay, That Grace is ſo diſpenſed, by way of judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial rectoral Diſtribution of Rewards, <hi>&amp;c. Pref. of the</hi> 1ſt <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Queſtion is, you ſay, Whether it pleaſed God to leave himſelf at liberty to juſtifie the Unbeliever, while ſuch, and glorifie the Unbeliever and Wicked, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o to damn the penitent godly Believer; this Mr. <hi>C.</hi> affirms, and I deny.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label>You ſhould have ſhewed the place where I ſaid it, that your Charge might have faſtned by a Demonſtration. I marvel you bluſh not at ſuch things as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Where have I that Expreſſion, of Gods leaving himſelf at liberty? Its one of your Terms of Art, not mine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he juſtifies the Ungodly, is what the Spirit of God ſaith; and therefore I may.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But I ſay in juſtifiing him, he ſanctifieth him; and whatever a Sinner is, he is juſtified as ſuch, not as made holy and ſanctified, unleſs you'l confound Juſtification and Sanctification as the Papiſts and Quakers do.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But when did I ſay, That God doth glorifie an Unbeliever, and a wicked Man; or damn the penitent and godly Believer? Or that in the Covenant of Grace he hath made any ſuch Exception, that he may or will do ſo? I ſuppoſe that you muſt mean by leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf at liberty.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95981:6"/>
            <p>"This, you ſay, is theſe Mens free Grace, while they deny the Goſpel Rule or Law. Theſe Taunts and Falſhoods are well enough, it ſeems, in your Mouth; its ſuitable to the reſt of the Prittle Prattle in this Preface.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <q>You ſay the Queſtion is not, Whether God hath not as to us abſolutely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and covenanted with Chriſt, that the Elect ſhall believe, and all Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving be pardoned, and ſo perſevere in Faith and Holineſs to eternal Life; which I affirm, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 5.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> Here then you allow that there is an abſolute Covenant of Grace (for whatever diſtinction you would make between the Covenant of Redemption and the Covenant of Grace, there's no Man of ſenſe can deny, that the Covenant of Redemption is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace) and if God hath abſolutely promiſed to, and covenanted with Chriſt, that the Elect ſhall believe and be pardoned, this muſt ſtand abſolute to the end of the World. But by your favour, tho' I am for the abſoluteneſs of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, yet it was not abſolute but conditional to Chriſt; that Faith and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Perſeverance, as promiſed to Chriſt for the Elect were conditional, and the condition was, that he ſhould make himſelf an Offering for Sin, bear it, and make full ſatisfaction to the Law by his Righteouſneſs Active and Paſſive, and make Interceſſion for Tranſgreſſors, and therefore tho' you affirm here, yet I deny.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But the Queſtion is (you ſay) whether there is a Covenant which requires our true believing conſent to the Terms of it, to the condition of Pardon and Glory, and ſuppoſeth this true conſent in the actual beſtowing theſe Benefits? This Mr. <hi>C</hi> denies, and I affirm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Reſ.</label> 1. I deny that there is any more Covenants of Grace than one, and ſay, That the Covenant between the Father and the Son, was that original Contract which was diſplayed and made manifeſt in the Goſpel of the old and new Teſtament, and in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is required in this Diſplay is abſolutely promiſed. For if there be two Covenants wherein the ſame things are promiſed, and to the ſame Perſons, the firſt abſolute and the ſecond conditional, the one muſt certainly be vacated by the other. For if I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to a Perſon, or to another for him, to give him a Houſe freely, and afterward make a covenant Bargain with him, that he muſt pay me 20 <hi>l.</hi> or 20 <hi>s. per annum,</hi> the firſt Covenant is vacated; or if I am bound to ſtand to my firſt Promiſe, the ſecond Agreement falls to the Ground. 2. Likewiſe obſerve what you affirm, That God hath made Terms as a Condition, <hi>i. e,</hi> federal of Pardon and Glory. So that here is brought in a Covenant of Works, to intervene betwixt the abſolute Covenant, and beſtowing the Benefits, abſolutely at firſt promiſed. Now Men may ſee plainly what you mean when you talk ſo much of Pardon for and by Jeſus Chriſt; this Pardon is one of the Benefits beſtowed in your new Law judicially, by way of remuneration to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Terms of Duty required.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <q>It is not whether Faith be the only Grace by which we receive and reſt on Chriſt for Juſtification, and that it is Chriſt received by Faith doth juſtifie, which is the ſenſe of the Proteſtants, when they ſay we are juſtified by Faith alone; this I affirm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> Yes you do in your ſenſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> That Chriſt juſtifies here, as much as is needful as to legal Righteouſneſs; but there is another Righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Evangelical, that puts in for a ſnack, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the new Law. And you do much miſrepreſent the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, for they ſay, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is all our Righteouſneſs, of one kind and another that we are juſtified by, a Righteouſneſs without us, and not by any within us, any Act or qualification whatever. But the Papiſts ſay with you, the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> doth anathematize </p>
            <q>
               <p>Thoſe that ſay a Man is juſtified without the Merit of Chriſt, by which Chriſt did merit for us, or is formally juſt by that, <hi>Anath.</hi> 10. And they curſe alſo any one that ſaith, that he is juſtified only by the Imputation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, or only by Remiſſion of Sins, without inherent Grace, <hi>Anath.</hi> 11.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95981:6"/>
            <p>But let's have the Query then; It is, you ſay, <q>Whether he that can truly believe to Juſtification, muſt be in part a convinced, penitent, humbled Sinner; and this you affirm, and ſay I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You ſhould have told the Place and my Words. Its poſſible I may deny it in your ſenſe, and I will prove how that you muſt deny it in my ſenſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> that legal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions and Humiliations are no federal conditions of Faith; for you ſay, That the firſt Grace is abſolutely given; and if ſo, there's no federal conditions of it. Why do you not bring in hearing the Word, as a federal condition of Faith, for it comes by Hearing? Why do you not bring in a Mans having his Senſes and Underſtanding, and many more things?</p>
            <p>And now you talk of Humblings, let me mind you what you ſay, <hi>Page</hi> 15. <q>You tell us of the Sum of the Popiſh Principles our Divines oppoſe. 1. They think that by Attrition (or a ſelfiſh legal fear of Puniſhment) Men do, <hi>ex congruo</hi> (or meetneſs) merit Charity and Faith, which be the beginning of Sanctification; and that this begun Sanctification is all our firſt Juſtification.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What do you ſay leſs than they, ſetting aſide the word Merit, and they ſay as to that <hi>de congruo</hi> its ſcarcely ſo? Nay ſome are againſt <hi>Meritum de congruo,</hi> as being any Merit but only a diſpoſition and meetneſs of the Subject, ſuch as you would have, and we may put their Attrition to your Humblings, as a meetneſs for Faith. See what the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaith, <hi>Can.</hi> 8. When <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <q>a Man is juſtified by Faith and <hi>gratis,</hi> it is to be underſtood becauſe Faith is the beginning, and the things that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede Juſtification are not meritorious of Grace:</q> See now how you abuſe the Papiſts. Nay I'l tell you more, for I would give the Devil his due; you abuſe the Papiſts in charging them for making this begun Sanctification all their Juſtification. The words of the 7th Canon of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> are, <q>That Juſtification followeth Preparation, which is not only remiſſion of Sins, but Sanctification:</q> And therefore they make not only Sanctification begun to be our firſt Juſtification. And in the 10th <hi>Anathema,</hi> they curſe them that ſay, <q>A Man is juſtified without the Righteouſneſs by which Chriſt did merit for us.</q> Now I think you ought to ask the Papiſts forgiveneſs for ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
            <p>Rhemiſts on <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3. they grant, That the beginning of our Juſtification, which they call the firſt, is meerly of Grace; neither can we do acceptable Works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be juſtified, but in the ſecond Juſtification, which is, the encreaſe of former Juſtice a Man may merit by good Works. So again they ſay, Works done of Nature before or without Faith, can't merit; but Works done by God's Grace, may and are joyned with it, as Cauſes of Salvation; and in theſe Points the Proteſtants oppoſe them. I could fill a Volume with it if need were, but its enough to ſay, you are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in telling us what the Proteſtants oppoſe them in.</p>
            <p>
               <q>You ſay alſo that I ſay, That Pardon is rather the condition of Faith, nay Pardon is the cauſe of Faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> I ſay rather, for if a federal condition muſt lye between giving and receiving, giving is the cauſal condition of receiving, and not receiving of giving.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Object muſt be before the Act of the Organ, Pardon is the Object applyed by Faith; Application before there is an Object, is <hi>contradictio in adjecto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Promiſe of Pardon is the Ground and Reaſon of our believing, therein is the Grace brought, therein doth the Truth and faithfulneſs of God appear; and the Apoſtle ſaith, Faith comes by hearing this Word of Promiſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> is wrought by it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. And he oppoſeth the Works of the Law, and the hearing of Faith in Juſtification <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2, 5. And what is that acceptation but of Faith, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15? And what doth it accept, but that faithful Goſpel ſaying there mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners, and the chiefeſt?</hi> Its the Grace of God working in this Promiſe, that hath wrought Faith in the hearts of thouſands</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95981:7"/>4. We ſay with all ſoundeſt Proteſtants, That Juſtification in Nature is before Sanctification and the Cauſe of it, and therefore of Faith, becauſe Faith as a Grace wrought, is a part of Sanctification. Its enough for you, to hold up that you call Error, and give it Name, and ſo let it go.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <q>It is not whether Sanctification taken ſtrictly do follow Juſtification; this I affirm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> If you affirm this, you ſhould not make ſo ſtrange of my ſaying, Pardon is the condition of believing. What you hide under ſtrictly I concern not my ſelf; Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is Sanctification, and if Juſtification goes before it, you allow it to be <hi>conditio ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> at leaſt. Therefore I conclude, Pardon is rather a condition, yea I ſay not meerly of Order, but ſuch a condition as is an influential Cauſe. But go on, ſtating your diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But whether effectual Vocation make a real habitual change in the Soul, and that this Vocation is in order of Nature before Juſtification: This Mr. <hi>C.</hi> and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and I affirm, with the Aſſembly.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> As to the Letter, I muſt tell your Anſwer to it is ſhort and ungenteel; and as he did <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who ſaid <hi>Bellarmine</hi> thou lyeſt; when you ſay, it was rather to ſerve a turn than to argue; it ſpake Truth weakly, and other things erroneouſly and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It juſtifies a neceſſity of dealing a little more roughly with Men of your Country and Kidney. But to our Point in hand; it need not be enquired, whether you take effectual Vocation in the active or paſſive Senſe, ſeeing you ſay its ſuch as makes a real habitual change in the Soul: And ſeeing it makes ſuch a change, it muſt be a change of Sanctification, and this, you ſay, is before Juſtification; how can that be, when you had ſaid before, that Juſtification is before Sanctification ſtrictly taken? What kind of Sanctification, I pray, is effectual Calling? Is it not ſo in a ſtrict ſenſe, when you ſay its a real habitual change in the Soul? Is this not turning from Darkneſs to Light, raiſing us together with Chriſt or being born again? But all this muſt be done before the Relative change; a Man muſt be free from the reigning Power of Sin, and alive from the Dead without Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. See what the Aſſembly ſaith in the larger Catech. Q. 67.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That effectual calling is the Work of Gods Almighty Power and Grace, whereby out of his free and eſpecial Love to his Elect, and from nothing in them moving him thereto, he doth in his accepted time, invite and draw them to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they are hereby made able and willing freely to anſwer his Call, and to accept and embrace the Grace offered and conveyed therein, <hi>i. e.</hi> then they are effectually called, when they have embraced the pardoning Grace of God offered and conveyed; </q> which ſhews the previouſneſs of that Grace working the effectual Calling conſummated in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and embracing the Goſpel offered; the Goſpel Grace in the Promiſe, is always that which works firſt upon the Sinner, moves his Heart, and draws it forth in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <q>11. It is not whether our ſincere Faith and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are imperfect, and ſo can be no meriting Righteouſneſs; which I affirm.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You affirm they are imperfect, and ſo do I; but not therefore that they can be no meriting Righteouſneſs; for the Merit of Righteouſneſs doth not depend upon the perfection of the Duty or Service in it ſelf, but its perfection in relation to the Law that requireth it; if the Duty required be never ſo weak, little, and lame, if I have ſuch a degree as the Law requires, its perfect as to that Law: The Law requires a poor Man to pay a Shilling to a Tax, its as good obedience as another Mans that's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to pay twenty. Many Inſtances might be given, the Papiſts ſay, Merit lies not in the value of the Action, but in Gods Acceptation. The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaith, Our Works are meritorious of eternal Life. <hi>Quia a patre acceptantur per Chriſtum,</hi> yea, ſaith S. <hi>de Clara, Actus meus dicitur meritorium quia elicitus ſeu Imperatus a gratia ex pactione divina acceptatur ad premium. Deus ab aeterno ordinavit hujuſmodi actus eſſe dignos vita eterna
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95981:7"/> quando eliciuntur a gratia habituali; non igitur tota ratio meriti a gratia ipſa.</hi> So <hi>Scotus, Actus non eſt meritorius praeciſe quia perveniens ex gratia, ſed quia acceptatur a Deo tan<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dignus vita aeterna.</hi> But where's the Queſtion then?</p>
            <p>
               <q>Whether Faith and Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are diſobedient even in a Goſpel account, and ſo uncapable of being Conditions of any of its promiſed ſaving Benefits?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> In the ſenſe of the Papiſts they be not, but be accepted of God for this end, to be federal conditions of a Law Covenant; they are perfect in that kind and relation, and merit the Benefit; but we ſay, tho' any of our Gifts of Grace or Duties are accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſt, yet they are not accepted to any Merit or Worthineſs of any other Grace; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral conditions and worthineſs of all Grace and Bleſſings beſtowed on us, are only in Chriſt; and hence Faith and Charity and other Gifts of Grace, tho' they have a conditional con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion one to another, yet they are all of Promiſe, and can't be federal conditions of any promiſed ſaving Benefits.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Mr. <hi>C.</hi> ſaith, I am againſt the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Aſſembly; I am ſure he'el never prove it, and I profeſs the contrary; but I am ſure he's againſt all the Confeſſions of Faith that we own as Orthodox.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> How your Principles agree with the ſaid Articles and Confeſſions, upon Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Examination, let others judg; 'tis not your ſaying, your profeſs the contrary, will ſatisfy the World, when <hi>res ipſa loquitur;</hi> eſpecially when you have the Confidence to ſuggeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a falſe thing of me in the ſame Breath, That you are ſure I am againſt all the Confeſſions of Faith that are orthodox (but indeed you ſay, which we call orthodox) that we, I ſuppoſe, are, you and your Schematiſts; and then what they account or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, I ſhall not trouble my ſelf. You go on and ſay, <q>In the Strength of Chriſt you'l ſuſtain the utmoſt Perſecution at the Hands of theſe angry Men; and while God enableth me, they ſhall not overturn the Goſpel by their unſcriptural Abuſe of the bleſſed Names of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and free Grace and the Goſpel way of Application.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Enduring Perſecution is no Infallible Argument that a Man's Principles are good; if it were, Papiſts and Quakers then have more to ſay for the juſtification of their Principles than ever you had, or are like to have; and let the wiſe judge, how near akin yours is to theirs: And whereas you inſinuate, as if you had ſuffered Perſecution from the angry Men (as you call them) who have conſcientiouſly contended earneſtly for the Faith. Impartial Men will (if they do weigh and conſider duly what you have done and ſaid in theſe Matters) determine which ſide hath been the Perſecutors, if Reproaches and falſe Imputations be Perſecution, and God will judge one Day whether you be a Champion (as you would be accounted) for Chriſt or againſt him; the Day will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal it; its not enough to brave it out before the World, a Judgment at Man's Day will not ſerve our Turns; he that judgeth you and I is the Lord, and therefore conſider what you do, while you call ſo much upon the Name of God and Chriſt, to countenance your confident undertakings in this Affair.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <q>there's a Myſtery in it that one Explication of a Text ſhould be pretended for a Reaſon againſt my whole Book, and ſo countenance all Dr. <hi>Cr.</hi> Errors, which they profeſs they diſlike.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Rep.</label> There's no Myſtery in it, that any faithful Miniſter or People ſhould not only be highly jealous of, but exceedingly blame ſuch a Book, and the Author which ſhall rob them of ſo high an Article of their Religion as the true Nature of the Doctrin of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and for the maintaining himſelf therein, muſt wreſt ſo eminent a Portion of Scripture out of their Hands as to its genuine and plain mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon which thouſands of the moſt eminent Saints in all Ages have lived, and do live; no, be you confident, they will not loſe that ſenſe of that Portion of Scripture (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.) which you oppoſe; they'll tug hard for it firſt, and it will ſtand in the Hearts and Prayers of God's Children maugre all Oppoſition. And whereas you ſay, you hear <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is of your Mind, He tell you what an Author of none of the leaſt Name
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95981:8"/> tells me, concerning <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Opinion: Thus <hi>Auguſtinus breviter oſtendit ab Apoſtolo,</hi> &amp;c. Auſtin <hi>briefly ſhews from the Apoſtle</hi> Phil. 3.9. <hi>that whatſoever is of his own Righteouſneſs is excluded there; and that</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaks not of the Law of Circumciſion or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but of the Precepts in which 'tis ſaid,</hi> Thou ſhalt not covet. <hi>Lydeker. de diſcr. legis &amp; Evangel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You proceed to vindicate yourſelf againſt the Charge of not being againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Confeſſion, and pitch upon the Doctrin of Imputation for an inſtance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you know you differ from them; and your ſtating your Judgment in that Point ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently evinceth, though you do it after that perverſe manner which is uſual with you, to make your Principles look ſound.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <q>You will ſtate that Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> of Imputation. 1. It is not whether Chriſt was a publick Perſon, as a Mediator in his Undertakings, and ſo tranſacted all for Sinners, that they might be pardoned and ſaved by his undertaken Satisfaction and Merit: This I affirm; but whether we are ſo repreſented in Chriſt, as that we are in Law Senſe; they that undertook to atone and merit; this I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> What do you mean by a publick Perſon, as a Mediator? Did he ſtand in ſuch a Capacity as to repreſent, undertake for, and ſtand in ſtead of the Elect? were they federally in him as his Seed? for ſo the Aſſembly ſay they were. See <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. <q>He was made the Head and Saviour of his Church, the Heir of all things: Unto whom God did from all eternity give a People to be his Seed.</q> So <hi>Larg. Cat.</hi> The Covenant of Grace was made with Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him with all the elect, as his Seed: But you ſay he only tranſacted for Sinners as a Mediator; but do you mean ſuch a Mediator as is a Surety; if ſo, the Perſons for whom he is a Surety are federally in him, for he takes the Debts upon him, ſtands in their room and ſtead, and they federally in him accounted, and to all Intents and Purpoſes he is entertained, as comprehending all their Debts in him. A Man may be a Mediator, and treat with both Parties at Variance; but not take the whole cauſe upon, ſo as to treat and engage, and make Payment in the Room of the offending Parties. But let us hear what your Queſtion is.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Whether we are ſo repreſented in Chriſt, that we were, in Law Senſe, thoſe that undertook to atone or merit? this I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> I will appeal to all Men of Senſe in the World, whether they can tell by your ſtating this Queſtion, whether you own or deny Chriſt to be a publick Perſon, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Elect. He is a publick Perſon as Mediator, and repreſents ſo as no body ever ſaid any perſon did repreſent another: <hi>viz.</hi> That we are, in Law Senſe, they that undertook to atone and merit. A perſon comes to be bound, as ſurety, to a Creditor for an hundred Debtors in <hi>Ludgate;</hi> he becomes Debtor, and is accepted in the room of all and every one, they all pay, and are diſcharged in him: Doth the Law reckon that all theſe Men were Sureties, or that they atoned or merited? but that in the Surety's Atonement and Merit, they being all repreſented by him, their perſons are accepted, and their Debts paid. Doth any Body look upon the Debtor to be the Surety becauſe the Surety ſtands bound? Or becauſe the Surety pays or undertook to atone and merit? I would fain know whether this be not perverſe perplexing a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion inſtead of ſtating of it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. You go on, ſtating thus: <q>Nor whether Chriſt was a Surety for us, in a Bond of his own, to pay our Debt to the full (or more) that we might in a due Time and way be releaſed?</q> This I affirm.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Reply.</label> If Chriſt came under Obligation to pay our Debt abſolutely, he repreſented not as if he obtained our releaſe but conditionally, upon future Terms to be performed by us or ſome others; for then his Suretiſhip was not for us, but to purchaſe Conditions for us.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But whether we were joynt Parties in one and the the ſame Bond with him, and ſo we were actually acquitted when he made ſatisfaction? therefore God could enjoyn
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95981:8"/> no Terms of Application to us for Juſtification and Glory, nor ſuſpend the ſame upon thoſe Terms. This I deny.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> What mean you by joynt Parties in one and the ſame Bond? do you mean the Bond of Debt to the Law, by reaſon of the Obligation of Doing and Suffering? there we ſtood bound as Principles, and not being able to diſcharge, Chriſt became bound as Surety; we were never bound as Sureties nor Chriſt as the Principle. But if you mean that both were bound to pay the ſame debt, we do affirm it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What do you mean by an actual Acquittance? Is it not meet that he that hath his Debt ſatisfied, ſhould have an actual Acquittance, or their Surety for them? there's no Man pays a Debt, his own or anothers, but he will have an Acquittance, according to the Terms of Payment, if they were ſuch as you ſuppoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to purchaſe a Diſcharge upon other Terms. But you ſay, If Chriſt were actually acquitted, and the elect in him, God would not come upon new Terms with the Sinner for Juſtification and Glory; this is as much as to ſay, Chriſt paid a Fine for Sinners, that they might be brought to lower Terms with the Juſtice of God by a milder Law. How falſe are you, when you tell us, Your meaning is, That Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is our only juſtifying Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? whereas here you own, That it obtained not our full Diſcharge, but only the bringing us under new Terms; upon which Juſtification and Glory are ſuſpended; is not the Performance then of thoſe purchaſed Terms, our immediate juſtifying Righteouſneſs?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That which you affirm in this firſt part is pretty unintelligible, but according to my Underſtanding it amounts to no more than that Chriſt dyed <hi>pro bono noſtro</hi> only, which is conſiſtent with all the Socinian Notions of Imputation. But as that which you ſay you deny, I want it to be unriddled; <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>That Chriſt was joynt Covenant Party with all the elect, in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, ſo that they are legally eſteemed to make Satisfaction, and yield Obedience in his doing thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You ſeem here to ſuggeſt as if ſome did hold, That Chriſt was under <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, ſo as the reſt of his Poſterity was, and conſequently fell in him, as they did. Or do you mean that all the Elect in Chriſt ſatisfied the Law, as all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity brake it in him? and this I ſuppoſe you deny. Now, as unto this Point, if I have hit your Meaning, I will tell you what a great Divine ſaith in anſwer to a Socinian: <q>The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was by God's Inſtitution a publick Perſon (having ſhewed that God's Pleaſure is the firſt Rule of Righteouſneſs) hence in him ſinning the World ſinned. The ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is not only by God's Inſtitution a publick perſon, but alſo an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perſon, becauſe God: This publick Perſon doing and ſuffering was as much as if the World of the Elect had ſuffered. If the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> a finite Perſon, was by God's Inſtitution in that Act of Diſobedience, a World of Men, why ſhould it ſeem ſtrange that the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> being an infinite Perſon, ſhould be by God's Inſtitution in the courſe of his Obedience, as the World of the Elect? He being infinite, there needed no more than God's Pleaſure to make him the World of Men, yea ten thouſand Worlds. That which is infinite knoweth no bounds, but God's Will. The kind of his Obedience was legal, the ſame in Nature and Meaſure which we, by the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſtood bound unto. This his Obedience to the Law was more acceptable to God than the Diſobedience of <hi>Adam,</hi> was deteſtable; yea more acceptable than the Obedience of <hi>Adam</hi> (underſtanding both as publick Perſons) had he continued in the firſt Covenant.</q> 
               <hi>Nort.</hi> againſt <hi>Pinch.</hi> p. 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That which you affirm of the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs here, is no more than what you ſay every where, importing no more than as to its Effects; but your Expreſſion is ſtrange, in ſaying Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is reputed by God, as that which now plead; for our Impurity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſeems to import that it doth not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally plead, but that God is willing to reckon it a kind of Plea: So that the Imputation you here intend of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is to Chriſt himſelf, and not to the Sinner: But you tell us what you deny,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95981:9"/>
            <p>You ſay its this, <q>That it is imputed as our formal Righteouſneſs, and ſo we may truly plead, that we our ſelves, as Elect, did legally by Proxy as our Chriſt, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and merit all, and without the Interpoſal of the Goſpel Rule, we have a legal Title to glory by <hi>Adam</hi> s Covenant: This I deny, as that which exclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, makes Chriſts Sufferings needleſs, denies any proper ſatisf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction, and deſtroys Chriſtianity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Here 1. You ſeem to deny Chriſt's imputed Righteouſneſs to be our formal Righteouſneſs, for Chriſt's Righteouſneſs we reckon to be, as it were, the Matter of our Juſtification, and being imputed by an Act of Grace, becomes our formal as well as material Righteouſneſs; for if it become not by Imputation our formal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, its not our perfect Righteouſneſs; for Matter and Form are the eſſential Cauſes of the Effect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we in Chriſt, ſatisfied the Juſtice of God, I know no ſound Proteſtant but will affirm, and that legally. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith over and over, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs was our legal Righteouſneſs, but you will deny, that we legally ſatisfied in Chriſt: May not a Debtor plead that he legally paid the Debt in his Surety, tho' not with his own Mony?</p>
            <p n="3">3. You caſt Reproach upon the Suretiſhip and federal Headſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, by calling him a Proxy and Attorny, as our Surety and Repreſentative. A Proxy is Vicarious, an inferior Perſon that's imployed to do Buſineſs in the Name and by the Authority of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, ſo that he is his Vicar or Subſtitute. But is a Father, that pays a Sons Debts, and purchaſeth an Eſtate for him out of his meer Love, Pity and Compaſſion, the Sons Proxy? Or if a Man purchaſe an Eſtate for his Heirs for ever, is he a Proxy to the Children yet unborn? And yet their Eſtate is bought and paid for in him, the original Right and Title lies in him the Purchaſer. Or a rich Man, who undertakes for the Debts of an hundred poor Priſoners in <hi>Ludgate</hi> (ſuppoſe the King, or another great Perſon) out of meer Pity and Commiſeration, is he their Proxy? Is he not their Benefactor and Patron? I wonder how you can ſpeak theſe things without ſuſpecting your own Spirit, when you do ſo manifeſtly caſt Dirt upon Jeſus Chriſt; may not I juſtly ſay you banter the Doctrin of Imputation?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But you ſay Chriſt can't ſatisfie and merit for us, without the Interpoſal of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Rule; the meaning whereof is, That Chriſt hath not legally ſatisfied for us till we have done ſomething in conformity to the ſaid Rule, that may give validity to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Chriſt, and make it pleadable as ſuch; ſo that Chriſt hath neither ſatisfied nor merited, till we make up the Complement whereby it becomes legal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What mean you by a legal Right to Glory by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant? If you mean by Chriſts ſatisfaction and obedience to <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, we have our legal Right to Glory, we ſay it; for Chriſt is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs to every one that believes, and through his Righteouſneſs we have a Right to Glory by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant; Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is our legal Righteouſneſs, as it reſpects the Perfection and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God in that Covenant; and its our Evangelical Righteouſneſs, as its in the behalf of, and beſtowed upon undone Sinners.</p>
            <p>But you ſay this Doctrin excludes Forgiveneſs; Why? Becauſe it brings in Forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs meerly upon Chriſt's Righteouſneſs alone: But how makes it Chriſt's Sufferings needleſs? when it lays all upon the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, imputed as the Matter and Form of our Juſtification? Or how doth it deny proper ſatisfaction, when it makes Chriſt's Righteouſneſs all the ſatisfaction? And your Doctrin makes it but an improper and remote ſatisfaction, yea and imperfect. And laſtly, you ſay, it deſtroys Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: This is ſo groſs a Charge, as that it is to be exploded with Deteſtation; if the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, as our legal and evangelical Right and Title to Life and Salvation, deſtroys Chriſtianity, we may burn our Bibles. But you go on.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95981:9"/>5 You affirm, <q>That all ſinned and dyed in <hi>Adam,</hi> and in Chriſt are all made alive, owning Chriſt's influence, both real and publick, as before explained.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> All this is <hi>nihil ad Rhombum,</hi> you own not hereby the Imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> Sin to his Poſterity; but that Sin and Death are only Effects of <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Sin, <hi>i. e.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluential; you own not that all Men were legally condemned in <hi>Adam,</hi> as a publick fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſon, ſtanding in their ſtead: In the ſame manner you always ſpeak of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt, as influential to our Forgiveneſs; and that the imputation of it is only beſtowing the Effects. <q>But whether we were in Chriſt before Faith, as we were ſeminally in <hi>Adam,</hi> before we were born; which his federal Headſhip did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the being thus in Chriſt before Faith;</q> I deny.</p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> You here grant our ſeminal being in <hi>Adam;</hi> and that <hi>Adam</hi>'s federal Headſhip ſuppoſed it, and therefore we were ſeminally and federally in <hi>Adam</hi> before we were born. Why ſpeak you it not poſitively, whether it was ſo or no? That we were federally and ſeminally in <hi>Adam,</hi> and that our Sin and Death was in him; there we loſt original Righteouſneſs, and thence the Imputation of his very firſt Sin to all his Poſterity, by vertue of our federal ſtanding in him, and by reaſon of our being ſeminally in him, the corruption of the whole Nature was in him, and naturally deſcended to us? If it be ſo, why are not the Elect as to Righteouſneſs and Life in the ſame manner in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> federally and ſeminally before they believe, <hi>i. e.</hi> before they are born again, in him federally, as to Righteouſneſs, and ſeminally as to the new Nature, Chriſt being their Righteouſneſs and Sanctification, whereas the Apoſtle runs the Parallel ſo fully and plainly as he doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5?</p>
            <p>But all this is but ſhuffling the Cards to make People believe your Principles are what they are not; moſt of whom cannot tell what you hold, when you have darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confounded the Queſtion, by your manner of ſtating it: You ſay, I object againſt you the denying of the Doctrin of Imputation; why do you not deny the Charge, but only diſtinguiſh ſo upon it as to confirm it? If your Principles are Truth why do you not ſpeak them out (but fill us with your cloudy Expreſſions and Diſtinctions, which you charge us for) why ſpeak you not plainly, That you deny the Suretiſhip of Chriſt, as you know you do? That you deny Chriſt to be a publick Perſon, in the Senſe as the ſoundeſt Proteſtants have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways held him to be; which laſt you do here in effect poſitively do, That we were neither federally nor ſeminally in Chriſt before Believing: Which, if ſo, I am ſure you muſt deny the whole Doctrine of Imputation, and what you pretend to can be no more than what the Socinians do. And how can you ſay you are not againſt the Confeſſion, and I am, when the Aſſembly ſaith, <hi>Confeſſ. c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. That Chriſt is ordained of God the Head and Saviour of his Church,<note place="margin">
                  <p>See <hi>Pinchin</hi> the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cinian, and Mr. <hi>Norton</hi>'s anſwer, p. 353. Dialo, I grant that all M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nkind are one with <hi>Adam,</hi> by a natural Union, as proceeding from the ſame Root; but I fear Mr. <hi>Forbes</hi> doth ſtretch out our natural Union with <hi>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</hi> to a perſonal, to the end that he might make <hi>Adam</hi>'s perſonal Action to be ours by imputation. <hi>Norton,</hi> The ſcope of Mr. <hi>Forbes</hi> is to prove the Imputation of Chriſt's Paſſive Obedience, and that only in his Dea h, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Matter of our Juſtification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We conſent to Mr. <hi>Forbs,</hi> as to the Argument taken from the Compariſon, but diſſent from him as concerning the Reſtrictions, the Reaſon of the Compariſon being founded upon the Conditions of the Perſons and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, it holds betwixt ſuch Acts a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt and ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> acted as publick Perſons: <hi>Adom</hi> therefore being in that Act of Diſobedience, only a publ ck Perſon, hence that Act only is imput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto his Seed. But Chriſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing in all his Acts of Obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a publick Perſon, hence therefore all the Acts of Chriſt's Obedience are imputed to his Seed. As upon ſuppoſition, <hi>Adam</hi>'s continuing in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (becauſe he had then continued a publick Perſon) all the Acts of his Obedience, even to the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of perfect Righteouſneſs, had been imputed to his Seed, according to the nature of the Covenant of Works, unto their attaining of Juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ification by the Law. The Uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n between <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity was not perſonal, nor only natural, but myſtical: It was a Conjunction of the Perſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> and all contained i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Loyns, in one Spiritual Body, by the Inſti ution of God, whereby he was as their Head, they as his Members, to ſtand or fall with him ſtanding or falling</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> ſums up <hi>Pinchin</hi>'s Errors under three Heads. 1. In his denying the Imputation of the Sin, of the Elect unto Chriſt, and his ſuffering the Pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhment due thereunto, contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53 5, 6. thereby leaving the Elect to periſh in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Sin. 2. Denying that Chriſt, as Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-Man Mediator, obey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d the Law, and therewith that he obeyed it for us, as our Surety, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Matt.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.17, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.7. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8.7.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. thereby rendring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and inſufficient Saviour, and ſpoiling the Elect of Salvation. 3. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="7 letters">
                        <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>ation of Chriſt's Obedience unto Juſtification, contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y to <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>avi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l that are ungodly under an impoſſibility of being juſtified. 2. Deſtroying the very being of a Sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ht<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, by taking away the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Chriſt unto the Law, and Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are the Matter and Form <hi>i. e.</hi> the eſſe tial Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes of Juſtification. 3. Placing a Sinner's Righteouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Atonement or Pardon of Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſuch as in effect doth man f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtly not only d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny itſelf to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the effect of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enieth, yea defieth the very b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ator, by Obdience of Chriſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Law for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t holdeth u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ueth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Wrath of God abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> away your Saviour. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> takes away our R <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and Juſt ficat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. W at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus, Grace and Souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? And I am ſure thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f theſe Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, which he o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſeth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>; yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and more.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto whom he did from all eternity give a People to be his Seed, and to be by him in Time redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, called Juſtified, Sanctified, Glorified. In the ſame manner they ſpeak in the <hi>Larg. Catech. Q.</hi> 30, 31, 32. as above rehearſed. And in the <hi>ſhort. Q.</hi> 18. man's ſinfulneſs conſiſts in the guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Sin.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95981:10"/>
            <p>In the 39th. Page of your Book, you pretend to ſome Anſwers, to what I affirm in ſome things: As that I deny the Covenant of Redemption to be a diſtinct Covenant from the Covenant of Grace. I own it, and make good my denial elſwhere, therefore will not <hi>actum agere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You blame me, p. 40. for ſaying, p. 29. That Pardon is not promiſed to Faith and Repentance, as things diſtinct from the Promiſe, but Pardon is promiſed together with Faith and Repentance to the Sinner. And herein you ſay, <q>I confound a Promiſe of Grace, and promiſes made to Grace, and affirm the Goſpel Covenant is but one Promiſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repl.</hi> 1. I do affirm, That the Promiſe of the Goſpel in its Original Grant and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Nature is but one, as the Promiſe of the Covenant of Works was but one, <hi>viz.</hi> Life. So in the Covenant of Grace 'tis Life, the Spirit of God is expreſs in it, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This is the Promiſe which he hath promiſed us, even eternal Life.</hi> And 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This is the Record</hi> (or Teſtimony) <hi>that he hath given us, Eternal Life, and this Life is in his Son.</hi> Now Eternal Life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all Juſtification, Sanctification, Adoption and Glory. 2. I affirm that in this Promiſe is Juſtification, Faith and Repentance promiſed. 3. That in this Promiſe Juſtification, Faith and Repentance are inſeparably conjoyned. 4. That in and under this Promiſe are multitudes of Gifts beſtowed in a way of connexion one to another, and have their particular Promiſes pointing diſtinctly to them; but theſe Gifts are no federal Conditions one of another. 5. I ſay, If you ſpeak of theſe Gifts of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Life, as in a way of conditionality, 'tis Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is the proper federal condition of Life, and Pardon is rather the Condition of Faith and Repentance than they of Pardon. I ſay ſo again, 1. If Giving be the Condition of Receiving, 'tis true; but Giving is the Condition of Receiving, for Faith is but the Sinner's receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pardon: Is not the giving of Pardon then rather the Condition of Faith, which is the receiving of it, than Faith of Pardon? <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> 10.43. So for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: The Cauſe is rather the Condition of the Effect than the Effect of the Cauſe; but Forgiveneſs received by Faith is the Cauſe of all true Evangelical Repentance. See this ſaving Repentance and Remiſſion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th given by one Hand of Promiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. preached together by Commiſſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. How ſtrange ſoever you make of this Divinity, 'tis built on the Rock Chriſt Jeſus, and you cannot ſhake it, nor all the Devils in Hell. You ſay, I wretchedly miſtake the Nature of the firſt Promiſe, as if it excluded all Terms of our Intereſt in the Bleſſing of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95981:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I know not what the firſt Promiſe is, if it be not a Bleſſing; and if the firſt Promiſe be abſolute to us (as you ſay the firſt Grace is) then it excludeth all Terms to be wrought by us, to intereſt us in the Bleſſings of it, unleſs you intend that a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Man is to perform theſe Terms in his natural State; and then the firſt Grace is not abſolute: And as for the firſt Promiſe, concerning the Seed of the Woman, it was abſolute, and ſaved our firſt Parents as ſuch, for it was all their Goſpel as I know of, and therefore they by it had Remiſſion, Faith and Repentance, without bringing the two laſt into a federal Condition: For if God had intended to bring them in as ſuch, 'tis moſt likely he would then have mentioned them as ſuch, <hi>Adam</hi> juſt coming out of a Covenant with federal Conditions.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to what I ſay of a Legal Grant, you ſay 'tis out of my Element. Be it ſo, others may not judge it ſo, though you do: Mr. Antinomian ſaith, a Grant may be legal two ways, either by free Gift, from a Perſon's good Will and Pleaſure; and ſo God's giving us, both Grace and Glory is legal, becauſe it gives us an undoubted, unexceptionable Right. And a legal Grant is a Law Covenant Grant, when the Gift is beſtowed upon the performance of federal Conditions, as Grace and Glory is beſtowed in and for Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs; both theſe Grants we have firſt in Election, chuſing us in Chriſt; and in the eternal Compact between the Father and the Son. You ſay what I ſpeak of, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. will appear not to be eternal, but before many Ages, and not to exclude Goſpel Conditions. If Chriſt be our great Goſpel federal Condition, I ſay it doth not; for God's Purpoſe and Grace was given us in Chriſt, and were to be beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in and through him. But who told you that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, was but before many Ages, 'tis ſure before the Times or Ages of the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld; and what can be ſuppoſed to be ſo but Eternity, when Chriſt rejoyced in the Sons of Men, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. And I think I have a good Interpreter on my ſide: <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith, on <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. In his Judgment the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot be referred to the firſt Promiſe, made to <hi>Adam, Cen.</hi> 3. much leſs to that of <hi>Abraham:</hi> But, ſaith he, <hi>Ante tempora ſeculorum;</hi> before the Ages of the World, doth denote all ſeries of Time or Ages, <hi>i. e.</hi> before this World was, according to <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 17.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this Senſe runs the Aſſembly's Notes, <hi>Poole</hi>'s Anot. continued.</p>
            <p>What I ſay of the Goſpel's being no Law with Sanction, I ſhall not trouble the Reader with here, but handle it in its proper Place; and therefore paſs by all you ſay, p. 43, 44 and 45.</p>
            <p>As for what you ſpeak about that Poſition of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> I leave the Learned to judge, whether you have ſalved it: I ſhall hardly ſet that and other things in a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eater L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, unleſs you provoke me thereto, as you inſinuate by further Endeavours to ſet other Men in the Light or Dark, to as great Reproach as you can <hi>caſt upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke Mr. <hi>R. B.</hi> to ſpeak orthodoxly, by ſaying, p. 22. When once a Tranſgreſſor is ſentenced by a Law, he falls into the Hands of Perogative, and the Prince may do with him what he pleaſeth (<hi>i. e.</hi> either execute him or pardon him) God a ſo might have put Repentance into the Condition of the Law of Works, and ſaid, If thou doſt not eat, or repent of thy eating, thou ſhalt have thy Reward: You ſhould have added, the Reaſon of my ſo ſaying; it was upon your ſaying, The Law of Works admitted no Repentance: I tell you, If God had intended Salvation by a Law of Works, wherein Repentance ſhould have been a Condition, he might have put it in at firſt; but God never intended to accept Repentance as a federal Condition of any Covenant, nor our imperfect Condition: And ſo I ſay again, with a <hi>non obſtante</hi> all that you have or can ſay againſt it; And I muſt ſtand to that Rule which Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> takes from <hi>Cham. de deſcenſu, tom.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This great Principle is all-a-long to be kept in Mind, and occaſionally to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as in Anſwer to this Queſtion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 
               <q>What is the ſupreme and firſt Cauſe why Juſtice requireth, That Sin ſhould be rewarded with Puniſhment due thereunto, according to the Law?</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95981:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <q>The free Conſtitution of God, the principal and whole Reaſon of this Myſtery depends upon the good Pleaſure of God; for who can deny that God could have ſaved Man in another way? But he would ſave him thus, and no otherwiſe than thus. This ſerves not only as a Sword to cut, but as a leading Truth to looſe the Knots of Carnal Reaſon. The good Pleaſure of God is the firſt Rule of Righteouſneſs, the Cauſe of all Cauſes, the Reaſon of all Reaſons: And, in one Word, all Reaſons in one Reaſon.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And how doth this make the following Saying orthodox? <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>Being that Chriſt the Mediator, and Faith in Chriſt are only means of the Reſtauration of Men to God by Holineſs and Love, therefore it muſt be ſaid from the Nature of the thing, Faith, Holineſs and the Love of God, are more neceſſary to Salvation than either Faith in Chriſt or the Sacrifice of Chriſt himſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now if I had ſaid that this Poſition were God's Conſtitution, <hi>viz.</hi> that Holineſs and Love to God wrought in us, ſhould be more neceſſary Means of Salvation than Faith in Chriſt, or the Sacrifice of Chriſt, you had ſaid ſomething: Or that it were the Conſtitution of God, That Chriſt in all things ſhould not have the Preheminence, whether <hi>in genere cauſarum, mediorum vel finium,</hi> Col. 1.18, 19, 20. Therefore to ſay Holineſs in Grace or Glory is more neceſſary than Chriſt Mediator, is to magnifie the Creature above Chriſt, himſelf. But becauſe you ſay you would not have ſpoken the Words yourſelf, but endeavour to explain them as charitably as you can, I do not think it convenient to give you any further trouble about them; but I muſt remark, That it is not ſo fair in you to charge all upon me as my Senſe, which is ſpoken by an Interlocutor in a Dialogue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95981:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN ENQUIRY,</hi> Whether the Goſpel be a New Law?</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU begin thus. <hi>Reader, Though I did not once call the Goſpel a Law in all my Book, only in my Preface called it a Law of Faith; yet becauſe the whole of Mr.</hi> C<hi>'s Book runs on this, I ſhall inſiſt moſt on this Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>R.</label> Whether you called the Goſpel a Law or no, it matters not; I know you kept your ſelf here, as in many other Points within your Trenches, yet he that reads your Book is very blind, if he ſees not this to be the Corner-ſtone of your whole Scheme: And by your now appearing in a Defence of that Principle, as your profeſſed Opinion: You have not only dealt more candidly with your Reader than in your former Book, but alſo juſtified me to the World, in theſe things. 1. That I endeavoured faithfully to repreſent your Opinions, and did ſo in this Point. 2. That I wronged you not in ſaying, Your Art lay in concealing your Tenents from your leſs intelligent Reader, under Ambiguous and Equivocal Expreſſions, which I called by a plain Engliſh Name that you ſeem to be offended at. 3. In that I treated you under the Appellation of a <hi>Neonomian</hi> (which is an <hi>Antinomian</hi> in the trueſt Senſe) in that you have in this Reply profeſſedly owned yourſelf as ſuch, and ſubſcribed to the Truth thereof, which for your own Reputation I would not have had you to have done.</p>
            <p>In handling this Queſtion, I ſhall in the firſt Place remark upon your ſtating the Queſtion; and ſhew its true ſtate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall anſwer your Arguments, to prove the Goſpel a new Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall ſhew what Law and Goſpel is?</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall give my Arguments to prove, That the Goſpel is no new Law.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſhall ſhew the Beginning and Progreſs of this great Error; <hi>viz.</hi> That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is a New Law.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The ſtating of the Queſtion.</head>
               <p>SIR, you tell us, 1. In what Senſe you hold the Goſpel not a Law; and from thence it follows, That in a Senſe it is not a Law, and therefore in mine it may not be a Law.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You ſay, <hi>You do not hold that the Goſpel includes nothing beſides this Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95981:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Here is your old Tricking again: The Queſtion is about the Goſpel being a Law, and you ſay it includes ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thing that is not a Law; it includes the Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and abſolute Promiſes, as if the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtion were, Whether a Scabbard were a Sword? And you ſay, The Scabbard includes a Sword: But, by your Favour, a Law, as ſuch, can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot include an abſolute Promiſe, for there's no Promiſe but conditional in a Law; but yet an abſolute Promiſe may include a Law, as that, <hi>I will write my Laws in your Hearts. There may be</hi> (you ſay) <hi>Prophecies, Hiſtories, Doctrinals,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet theſe may be called Adjuncts.</hi> Of what? You ſhould have told us whether of Law or Goſpel, or of the Goſpel as a Law. The Hiſtories of Chriſt are Goſpel, and the Prophecies of him, and whatever in Doctrinals brings good News to Sinners, belongs to the Promiſe and Exemplification thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You ſay, p 19. <q>
                     <hi>Nor do I</hi> judge it a Law, in that Senſe our Divines ſix on S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians and Arminians.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> No, you apprehend our Divines abuſe them, but yet it hinders not but that you may judge it a Law, in the Senſe of the Socinians and Arminians: I have told what yours is, let the Reader judge whether it be ſo or no; for they hold Juſtification by Acts of Obedience to this Law but as you do: Nor do they hold that we are juſtified thereby, as <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have been by perfect Obedience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You ſay, <hi>Nor do I tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it in the Popiſh Senſe, which the Socinians and Arminians eſpouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> The Popiſh Senſe of Merit is renounced by the Socinians and Arminians, as well as by you, and as much, for ought I can ſee. The Popiſh Senſe is very plain from the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Anath. 20. Curſed is he that ſaith the Goſpel is a Promiſe, without a Condition of obſerving the Command: And this, I am ſure, is your Senſe. You proceed,</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>"It is not a Law that ſuppoſeth a moral ability in Sinners to perform its Precepts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Its an unreaſonable Law that requires Duty of thoſe that have no ability to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; and that Law that makes a Condition, and promiſeth Ability, concludes not the Subject till the Power is given; and, when all comes to all, 'tis but a comprehenſive Promiſe both of the Duty and Benefit to be received by it. You ſay,</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Its not a Law that extinguiſheth the Law of Nature, which hath its ſpecial Precepts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> If the Law of Nature be the Law of <hi>Adam,</hi> you ſay it vacates it: for if it ſtrip it of its Sanction it ceaſeth to be a Law, for Sanction is the Law's Ratification as ſuch. Again,</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Neither doth this Law require any thing of us as a Condition of Chriſt's coming into the World, nor of the firſt Grace to the Elect. This the Covenant of Redemption ſecures to the Catholick Church by Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Whoever talked of our doing any thing, as a Condition of Chriſt's coming into the World as our Redeemer, but believe it (as weak as you ſay Mr. <hi>C.</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ile preſume to tell you, that you are bold to attempt to prove the Goſpel to be a Law with Sanction: If you allow that the firſt Grace is abſolutely given, and what is given by electing Grace is ſecured by Election to the Elect; its an inconſiſtent Principle that Redemption ſecures nothing but conditionally, for where the abſoluteneſs of any thing is ſecured, it is ſecured ſo as to ceaſe to be conditional.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Nor is it a Law of Obedience, whereto it renders any promiſed Bleſſing a Debt; all is free though ſure; its free as to procurement or Price, yet it is as ſure by Promiſe as if it were by Debt: The Price was Chriſt's Obedience and Sufferings, all comes of Gift, yet in that way which God appoints to give it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> This amounts to thus much, That now you have dwindled your Law quite away; for that Obedience that renders not the Promiſe a Debt, can be no Law with Sanction: for by the ſame Reaſon that the Puniſhment is due to me upon Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the Promiſe is due upon Obedience. You ſay, Its ſure by Promiſe, ſo every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſory Covenant makes Bleſſings ſure; but that which is ſure and free, cannot be by Law Conditions.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95981:12"/>
               <p>P. 20. You give us a very long and confuſed account of your New Law, the ſum whereof is, That upon Believing and Perſevering in ſincere Faith and Holineſs, Life and Salvation is promiſed, and upon non-performance Death and Damnation threatned. The Senſe is, Do and live; the very ſame Eſſentials as to Matter and Form; the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Duties and Promiſes, or Sins and Puniſhment; the Form is the connection of theſe together by the Sovereign of Authority of a Law giver. You ſay, <q>That you mean by ſaying, The Goſpel is a Law, that God in Chriſt commands Sinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt with a true operative Faith.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> We grant the Goſpel doth ſo command, but is it a Condition required of the Creature, to be performed in and by his preſent Abilities? Muſt he have this firſt Grace given before he perform the Condition, and by him that commands it? Yet muſt this Command be a Law with Sanction? No, this Command carries with it to the Elect nothing but a gracious Offer and Invitation, and effectual operative Means to bring a poor Sinner from under a Law with Sanction, to Life and Salvation: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>The Wages of Sin is Death:</hi> He lies under this Law-condemnation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>He is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already:</hi> The Goſpel calls him not to come under another Condemnation, but it calls him to the Gift of God; What's that? Eternal Life through Jeſus Chriſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides God's Commands in the Goſpel are gracious, its to ſuch Duties which the ſame Grace promiſeth, and there's no middle between being under the Law and under Grace, under a gracious Command and a legal, they are <hi>adverſa ſine medio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>vpon their believing they ſhall be united to Chriſt;</hi> therefore they muſt firſt do ſomething before Union to Chriſt, that they may have the Benefit of Union, make the Fruit good, and then the Tree afterward, contrary to one of the fundamental Maxims of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. You proceed and ſay, it threatens, <hi>if any dye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing, impenitent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they ſhall be barred from theſe Benefits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> The meaning is, They ſhall die under the Condemnation of the Law they are in already; as much as to ſay, a Phyſician offers a Sick Patient a Remedy, he refuſeth it, and dies of his Diſeaſe, will you ſay the Phyſician brought him under a Law, with Sanction? Many ſuch Inſtances might be given; The King ſends a Pardon to all the condemned Priſoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> ſuppoſe it be upon condition of Acceptance; ſome one accept not, will the Court now try him upon a new Law? No; there's no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tryal, he is executed upon the Sentence before received: And ſo are all thoſe Places to be underſtood that ſay, <hi>He that believes not ſhall be damned:</hi> If you ſay by what Law: I ſay not by a new one, but by the Old Law. I own, as I believe there are degrees of Glory, according to the degrees of the Veſſels of Honour greater or leſſer; ſo there are degrees of Wrath, which the Law will execute according to the degree of Sin; and the Law will look upon rejection of Chriſt, as the higheſt degree of Diſobedience: Therefore are thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>It ſhall be more tolerable for Sodom than for Corazin;</hi> ſome ſhall be beaten with fewer, ſome more Stripes; ſome counted worthy of ſorer Puniſhments than others; but all this is by the Law, not by the Goſpel: And Unbelief and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency are Sins Judged and Condemned with all their Aggravations, ſeverely enough, by that Law, you need not doubt; there needs no new Law to do it. Your referring yourſelf to the Aſſembly will caſt you, for they never intended any ſuch thing, that the Goſpel is a Law.</p>
               <p>You ſay, 1. <hi>Here's the Eſſentials of a Law, God is our Ruler and we his Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Are Ruler and Subjects the Eſſentials of a Law? that's ſtrange Logick: The Ruler in his legiſlative Power is the efficient: and ſo in his executi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, in application of it to its Ends, and the ruled are therefore called Subj cts, becauſe under Subjection to both; the Law is eſſentially diſtinct from both. Put go on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Will revealed in a way of Governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, here's the Precept that binds to Duty; here's a Promiſe made to them that comply, and a Threatning denounced againſt ſuch as rebel.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95981:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> Theſe look like Eſſentials of a Law of Works, ſuch was <hi>Adam</hi>'s Law, there was God's Will for Duty in a way of Government revealed, a Promiſe to him if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, and a Threat denounced, in caſe he did not: Now then, that Law which hath all the Eſſentials of a Covenant of Works, is a Covenant of Works; but your new Law, by your Deſcription, hath all the Eſſentials of a Covenant of Works.</p>
               <p>Therefore you ſay 2. <hi>This is a Law of Grace, and its made by our Redeemer for fallen Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Say you ſo? 1. That which is made and executed in a way of Judicial Proceeding, is not a Law of Grace; for Grace and judicial Proceeding is diametrically oppoſite: But you ſay it's a Law in a way of Government, by a Law therefore of Judicial Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 2. You ſay its made by our Redeemer: Is it made with our Redeemer? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you muſt mean ſo, becauſe you ſay for fallen Man; then Chriſt covenanted in our ſtead, which you deny elſewhere, and he is to perform the Conditions for us. 3. You ſay, <q>All the Benefits of it are founded on Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, as the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Cauſe of them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> And where are the Duties founded in Man's Natural Power and Will? No; youl ſay in Election abſolutely as to the firſt Grace: Well then, here's the Benefits ſecured in Redemption, abſolutely I hope, and the firſt Grace in Election: Now if you can tell us where to get Security for after Graces and Perſeverance, we ſhould have this whole Covenant abſolutely ſecured. Effectual Ability to perform the Duty (<hi>i. e.</hi> the firſt Duty) is provided for, you ſay, in Election: But is after Duties provided for there? if ſo, election is the ſole Covenant Condition for Duty and Redemption for Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits: Thus you may mangle the Grace of God.</p>
               <p>Again, you ſay, <hi>God doth not fix on theſe Terms for any Worth in them, or Profit to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Its true he did not fix on <hi>Adam</hi>'s Terms for any Worth in them; what proportion could the forbearing an Apple bear to eternal Life, or what Profit would it have been to God, if <hi>Adam</hi> had let the Apple hang on the Tree, or perſevered all his Days in Holineſs?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W. The Goſpel is the Inſtrument or Sign by which this Will of God is expreſſed; this is not the Language of God in</hi> Adam's <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> An Inſtrument in this Senſe is a Law, Deed or Conveyance, engroſſed or enrolled, which is but a ſmall adjunct to the Law. The Scripture of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are called Inſtruments, becauſe they are the enrollments of this Will of Chriſt and his Teſtament ratified by his Death; and you ſay the Goſpel is a Sign, the Seals of the Covenant are Signs, but the Covenant of Grace is not a Sign, unleſs you mean it ſignifies God's Will and Pleaſure in Government, and ſo did <hi>Adam</hi>'s Law, and was the Language of it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W. It ſixeth that Rule of the Promiſe, which Mr.</hi> C. p. 33. <hi>is at a loſs to know.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> And ſo are more than I: for you ſay, Its not the Promiſe nor the Precept, where to find a Rule for the Promiſe in the Law, I know not, if it be not in Promiſe or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, will you ſay its the connection of Precept and Promiſe? if ſo its the Rule rather of the Law, <hi>forma perquam lex eſt;</hi> is it God's Rule to diſpenſe by, or our Rule to claim by? it may be you mean both, Precepts and Promiſes are <hi>deſparata</hi> at leaſt, therefore what your new Term is, I ſuppoſe you do not know what it is yourſelf, no more than your other new Rules of Sin, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and miſery, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Since in ſtead of clearing the Ouſtion you have confounded it, I will take the true ſtate of it from a Man that would ſpeak his Mind more intelligeably in theſe Matters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Queſtion ſtated.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scrip. G. Juſtific. Contr.</hi> 17. <q>My true Senſe is, That the Covenant of Grace is ſuch a Law, as that the ſincere Acts of Faith and Obedience, and perſeverance therein are the Conditions upon which eternal Life and Salvation is promiſed, with a Penalty of eternal Death, threatned upon the non-performance; only I ſay that ſincere Faith and Repentance are the moral qualifying Conditions of the Continuance of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95981:13"/> our juſtification and enjoyment of Heaven.</q> And this is a true Account of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how yourſelf underſtands the Goſpel to be a new Law; as I could prove from your own Expreſſions, even to every word here in this Account, you might therefore have ſpared yourſelf and me the labour about your confuſed ſtating the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Before I anſwer your Arguments, I ſhall promiſe a few things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. It being a great End of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the Covenant of Grace, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore fallen Man, and in ſo doing to magnifie the Law, he makes full atonement for the breach of it, brings in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, procures New Obedience to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive part of it, teacheth it by his Grace, and works it by his Spirit; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the Covenant of Works, Obedience was the Way to, and Condition of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, he makes the Promiſe the Way to, and Condition of Obedience, commanding no more than what he hath promiſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we ſay the Goſpel is not a New Law with Sanction, we deny it not to be a Teſtament that hath its ratification in the Death of Chriſt the Teſtator, wherein alſo the Law of Works had its Sanction, in reſpect of Penalty, for all thoſe that ſhall be ſaved by him, as to ſatisfaction for their ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Rule and Government which Chriſt exerciſeth over his Church, as it comes to him by right of Redemption, ſo that Obedience we give to him is part of that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life which he hath purchaſed and reſtored to us, and both his government and our ſubjection thereto is of Promiſe, and none of the leaſt Bleſſings and Priviledges of the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As the Matter of all Precepts, requiring Sanctity and Obedience of Heart and Life, moral and inſtituted, abſolutely conſidered, primarily belong to the firſt Law of Works, and ſo are binding in a natural relation unto Unregenerate and Regenerate, as they are the Commands of God the Creator, and the leaſt Tranſgreſſion requires a Puniſhment due to the Breach of the whole Law; So our Obedience becomes Goſpel-Obedience, 1. From our being reſtored to it in Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> 2 In that it flows from a new Life given, we muſt live before we can do. 3. From the end of performance, it's not for Life, as a Law-Reward of it, but for the ſake, honour, duty to, and enjoyment of Chriſt, and in the moſt grateful returns of his grace and love to us. 4. It's performed from higher Motives and Obligations, <hi>viz.</hi> that great Love wherewith God hath loved us, conſtraining us to the higheſt love and expreſſions thereof to him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As for all Sin and Diſobedience (even Impenitence and Unbelief) to any Commands of the Goſpel, it's condemned by the Law; and every one under the condemnations of Impenitence, Unbelief, rejection of Chriſt, or diſobedience in a Natural Eſtate, are therein under the Law; but there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mean to their Perſons, tho' all their Sins alſo are condemned by the Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. I proceed now to your Arguments.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s Arg 1. <hi>The Goſpel is called a Law, by the Spirit of God,</hi> Iſa. 42.4. Mic. 4.2. Rom. 3.27. Ch. 10.31. Jam. 1.25. and 2.12. Pſal. 19.7. Gal. 6.2. Rom. 8.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> As to the places quoted out of the Old Teſtament, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.4. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19 7. I have ſhewn, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies Doctrin, and Inſtruction, and ſometimes is taken for the whole revealed Mind and Will of God in the Word, and it's called by the Name of Law, as a part for the whole, both Law and Goſpel, in that place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.4. a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Chriſt; it's a Promiſe, that the Iſles ſhall wait for Chriſt's Doctrin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all Commands from Chriſt, whoſe Precepts may be called Laws, tho' of another nature than a Law with Sanction; the preceptive parts of the Goſpel are often called Laws, eſpecially in the Old Teſtament; but this makes not the Goſpel itſelf a Law, tho' it contain many Precepts. That of <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. hath the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; thoſe places explicate themſelves by the Word of the Lord: <hi>The law ſhall go forth of Zion, and the word of God from Jeruſalem.</hi> So that Law ſignifies no more than the Word preached, both Law and Goſpel; it were eaſie to ſhew how it's uſed at large in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95981:14"/> 
                  <hi>Proverbs</hi> and <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and elſewhere, not under any diſtinct conſideration of Law or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. We have ſhewed the Covenant of Grace is exhibited only in a way of promiſe and free-gift unto ſinners, as ſuch, takes them into Covenant with God, not upon any terms of their doing, perfect or imperfect, performed in their own or another's ſtrength, tho' it takes them into the Kingdom where Chriſt: rules and governs them, and from which Kingdom goes forth all the Word of the Lord, both Law and Goſpel. Laſtly, The Old Teſtament ſpeaks often prophetically of the Goſpel in its own Terms and Dialect, as by Prieſts, Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 66.21. c. 56.7. c. 6.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40. c. 41, 42.</p>
               <p>That of <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. where the Apoſtle ſaith, that boaſting is excluded; by what Law? By the Law of Faith, it may be taken for an ordinary rhetorical <hi>figura dictionis,</hi> called <hi>Anadiploſis;</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith, the Apoſtle doth here, <hi>de induſtria</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſay, the Law of Faith, inſtead of Faith, becauſe the adverſaries of Grace were always wont to have the Name of the Law in their mouths, for which reaſon our Lord calls Faith, a Work, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.29. and on which place he ſaith, they are plainly ridiculous, who from hence will argue, that Faith is a Wo k, and that therefore we are juſtified by Works. But if any that contend for a further account of the meaning of this Expreſſion, 1. It is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin of Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt's Righteouſneſs which he oppoſeth to all Law-Righteouſneſs, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. or other Doctrin that teacheth contrary. 2. It may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the nature of Faith, the power and efficacy of it; the nature of it and its power in the Soul, is to make a Man renounce all inherent righteouſneſs; in the ſame ſenſe is Law taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. the Law of the Spirit of Life that is in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>viz. i. e.</hi> the nature, power, and efficacy of it. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. The Law of Sin is no more than the power and prevalency of it, whereby it captivates us. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25. The Law of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is no other than the Goſpel-Doctrin of Freedom by Jeſus Chriſt, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 8.36.) from the Law Moral and Ceremonial for juſtificaion, yea, he ſpeaks to them as ſuch (ſaith <hi>Beza</hi>) on whom no Yoak of Ceremonial Bondage was laid, (as <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 15.10.) yea, ſuch as the Moral Law could not retain as Servants under fear, but the Spirit of God forms them into free and voluntary Obedience. Hence it's plain enough, that the Apoſtle oppoſeth the Goſpel to a Law with Sanction, which enforceth obedience from the threats thereof. So <hi>Beza</hi> carries, <hi>c.</hi> 2.12. <hi>This Epithite of Liberty,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is very fitly added,</hi> [Having ſhewed he ſpake of the Moral Law before, which he called the Royal Law in its full Sanction, as appears from <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, 10.] <hi>for ſeeing we are made free by the Son, by a much better right the Lord requires of us the Fruits of Righteouſneſs, rather than of thoſe who remain under the Tyranny of the Law of Sin,</hi> &amp;c. So that from theſe Expreſſions of <hi>James,</hi> here is ſo little pretence for a Plea to make the Goſpel a Law with Sanction, that the Apoſtle ſeems ſtrenuouſly to argue againſt it.</p>
               <p>I wonder that place is mentioned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31. the Law of Righteouſneſs, is plainly the Law of Works; for it was Righteouſneſs by this Law they ſought after, but loſt their labour, not ſeeking after a Righteouſneſs to ſatisfie the Law by Faith in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>You argue alſo from <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. <hi>This is ſpoken of a particular Precept,</hi> [which are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently termed Laws or Inſtructions] <hi>Bear one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfil the law of Christ,</hi> or his Command, yea, from an Obligation ſo to do (an Obligation to Obedience and Thankfulneſs is ſometimes called a Law of Love.) And what was the obligation? Chriſt bore our burdens. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. Therefore we ſhould bear one anothers burdens, as he carried our griefs and ſorrows: <hi>Be followers of Christ as dear children. Beza</hi> and others refer it to <hi>John</hi> 13.34, 35. <hi>A new commandment give I unto you, that you love one another as I have loved you, i. e.</hi> I give you a new Motive and Principle to act Obedience from: and this is contrary to a Principle and Spirit of Bondage and Fear from a Law with Sanction; and this New Commandment is called the Old, as to the Matter of it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. <hi>Mens behaviour towards the Goſpel is expreſſed by words that denote it to be a Law.</hi> Rom. 10.16. 2 Cor. 9.13. 2 Theſſ. 1.8. 1 Pet. 4.17.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95981:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> You ſaid, tho' the Goſpel be a Law with Sanction, yet it contains in it abſolute Promiſes. This I deny, as a contradiction. But I affirm, that an abſolute Promiſe may contain in it Law-Precepts, as that Promiſe, <hi>I will w ite my laws in your hearts;</hi> the Goſpel ſets up the Law-Precepts as Rules of Sanctity and Obedience, and calls for a conformity to them from better Motives and Principles; yet upon bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Promiſes, not ſuch as provoked to obedience, by rewarding the work performed in our own ſtrength, but ſuch as promiſed the very obedience it ſelf. Therefore no body denies obedience to the Goſpel, and ſubjection to it from the grace of Adoption, as Children, not as Slaves under the rigour of a Law. Thoſe places that ſpeak of taking venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them that obey not the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. they ſhew only that the curſe of the Law will fall more heavily upon them for diſobedience to God in the Goſpel, Impenitency and Infidelity being Sins the Law of God doth condemn and judge; and Chriſt will come at the laſt day clothed with Law-Vengeance, which is called <hi>flaming fire,</hi> and will proceed againſt all ſinners, thoſe that are ignorant of God, and thoſe that are diſobedient to the Goſpel, and judge them by one and the ſame Law, tho' ſome that have added to their other ſins the rejection of Chriſt, and ſo lye under aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their ſins, and are become more inexcuſable, may be accounted worthy of ſorer degrees of puniſhment, and judged thereto by the ſame Law.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>Juſtification is a Judicial Act, therefore it muſt be by a Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> You ſhould have formed your Argument, and then it would have run thus: It Juſtification be a Judicial Act, then the Goſpel muſt be Law; but Juſtification is a Judicial Act: Therefore, 1. I deny the Conſequence of the Major; for it may be a Judicial Act in reſpect of the firſt violated Law; firſt a gracious Act of imputing Chriſt's righteouſneſs to us that may anſwer the demands of that Law, and then a Judicial Act of acquitting us from the condemnation of it, accounting us in this manner righteous by this Law; and therefore there's no need of another Law for our juſtification, tho' it be a Judicial Act. You ſay in Juſtification is a right to Impunity: and can any thing but a Law give this? but I tell you, it muſt be the Law that's offended, muſt diſcharge in a way of juſtice from puniſhment, and not another Law, unleſs the Pardon be by prerogative or repeal</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. <hi>The Goſpel gives a right to its Benefits upon believing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> The Goſpel gives nothing but benefits to ſinners; Faith is one of the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and there's a connexion of benefits of different nature in the Goſpel-gifts, but our right to all as a federal condition is in Chriſt, and it's ſafe enough to ſpeak of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Worthineſs and Rewards, but they are founded in Chriſt, not in any Law-Righteouſneſs of ours.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. <hi>If God have no Goſpel-rule, beſides Election and diſtinguiſhing Mercy, to confer glory by, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n God will not, nay cannot ſave the non-elect, tho' th y ſhould believe in Chriſt. Say not they will not believe, hath not God declared he will ſave them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they believe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Firſt, Here you change the terms, putting Rule for Law, and God's Rule for Man's; therefore you conclude not the Queſtion. 2. You make a Pro ſyllogiſm. Your Argument ſhould regularly run thus: If God hath Goſpel-rule, beſides Election and diſtinguiſhing Mercy, to confer glory by, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Goſpel is a Law; but God hath other Goſpel-rules to confer glory by, beſides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore, 1. Your Conſequence is denied; for if you will have God's way of conferring grace or glory to be a rule to him, the particular application thereof depends wholly upon his good will and pleaſure and the manner it ſelf, and that's the rule of all rules; and ſo the rule of conferring grace and glory is all one: But ſuppoſe God's manner of conferring glory be the rule you mean, God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver propounded but two ways of doing it, one in a way of free grace and abſolute promiſe, and the other in a way of debt to us by a rule of juſtice; now your Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will ſink, for God's rule in beſtowing grace and glory upon ſinners, is to do it in a way of free grace by promiſe and gift, and not in a way or by the rule of a Law or diſtributive Juſtice. 2. For your Minor it's this, That God hath a Goſpel-rule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95981:15"/> Election and diſtinguiſhing Mercy, to confer glory by; which you prove thus, If God hath not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then he cannot nor will not ſave the non-elect if they believe: But he will ſave the non-elect if they believe; therefore, this Argument neceſſarily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, that God hath a Rule of Salvation altogether independent on Election and diſtinguiſhing Mercy, whereby others may be ſaved if they will; and you take it for granted, that the non-elect will believe, for you ſay, ſay not they will not believe. Your Minor is flatly denied, for that general Propoſition, <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not that a non-elect perſon ſhall believe or be ſaved, it's falſe Logick ſo to do; there's no more in it than in this Propoſition, Every Man is a rational Creature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a Horſe be a rational Creature, he is a Man. This connex Propoſition hath a verity in the connexion, but determins not any truth in the antecedent or conſequent, that a Horſe will ever be a Man or a rational Creature. So here, he that believes ſhall be ſaved; therefore then, if the non-elect believe they ſhall be ſaved; if <hi>Judas</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he ſhould be ſaved, but this ſays not that <hi>Judas</hi> will believe or be ſaved. Yet you ſay, hath not God declared he will ſave them if they believe? I ſay, no where, he hath not ſaid, I will ſave a non-elect perſon if he believe, more than he hath ſaid a Horſe ſhall be a Man if he can uſe reaſon or ſpeak, or a Man ſhall be a Horſe if he have four feet. There's hundreds of ſuch Inſtances: The fire conſumes all combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; if I throw my Coat or Cap in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the fire it will be burnt; but this doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin that I will throw it into the fire, or that it will be burnt, but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary that there will be neither one nor the other: Therefore how bold and illogical is it for you to conclude, that God will ſave the non-elect upon an imperformable condition? for whatever hath no other foundation than an impoſſible condition, can never be; but the ſalvation of the non-elect can be founded upon nothing but an impoſſible condition; for it can have no other condition, according to you, but believing, and this is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, becauſe, according to you, alſo Faith is from Election, and therefore it's a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to talk of ſaving non-elect, or God's making a Rule to ſave them upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their having that which he never intended to give them. The general Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition runs thus, All Men that ſhall believe ſhall be ſaved; a general contradiction here will not divide truth from falſhood, <hi>Viz.</hi> No Man ſhall believe therefore no Man ſhall be ſaved; but to divide truth from falſhood and fix it on a ſubject, the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction muſt be ſpecial or proper, and then that general Axiom and Application, ſpecially or properly, makes this Syllogiſm, All Men that believe ſhall be ſaved; ſome Men ſhall ſhall not believe, as non-elect, or <hi>Judas,</hi> therefore ſome Men ſhall not be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Now ſee how well you agree with the Aſſembly in this Point, <hi>ch.</hi> 10. §. iv. they ſay <q>non-elect ones, tho' they may be called by the Miniſtry of the Word, and may have ſome common Operations of the Spirit, yet they never truly come unto Chriſt, and therefore cannot be ſaved.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You ſay <hi>Forgiveneſs is an act of Soveraignty,</hi> and how you will reconcile that to what you ſay before and after. I know not. 1. That it's a judicial Act by a rule of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; if ſo, it's not in that reſpect a ſoveraign Act, wherein God is free to give faith and forgiveneſs to whom he will. And, 2. You ſay, he hath not left himſelf free to give forgiveneſs to whom he will of the adult, without faith, and therefore God muſt come under a Law to give forgiveneſs in the way of a Law, whereas the ſame ſoveraign grace that enclines him to one doth alſo to the other, and both faith and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are the free gift in the Promiſe, in a way of ſhewing forth his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. <hi>The Apoſtles, with all the Saints, may be arraigned, as fallen from Grace, and turned from the Goſpel, if it be no Rule, according to which God applies Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, How ſhould</hi> Peter, <hi>ſay,</hi> Repent and be baptized?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> I ſee no Conſequence here at all; the Argument, to me, ſeems to run thus: Either the Goſpel is a new Law with Sanction, or elſe the Apoſtles are fallen from Grace: And what's the reaſon of this forced Argument? The Apoſtles preached, <hi>That
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95981:15"/> Men ſhould repent and be baptized.</hi> I hope you will make Baptiſm too to belong indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably to the new Law, as a Condition; but I pray, doth the Goſpel, requiring and call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Goſpel Duties, make the Goſpel a new Law with Sanction? Are not Goſpel Duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es from Goſpel quickning and enlivning a poor dead Sinner to obey, the Goſpel Commands of Chriſt to an Unbeliever? He doth not deal with him as a Perſon under a moral Power to anſwer them, and therefore putting him under tryal by his natural ſtrength, as all Laws do; but Goſpel Commands are as Chriſt's Voice to <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the Grave, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.25. I pray by what Law are dead Men capable of coming to Life? The Goſpel is the power of God to Salvation, not the power of Man. You alledge the Gaoler's words, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.36. <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved.</hi> I wonder you ſhould inſiſt upon the words of a Man that knew not Chriſt, and knew no other way of Salvation than by doing. <hi>Paul</hi> indulged him not in this Opinion, but taught contrary, exhorting him to believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which the Apoſtle always oppoſed to doing; Faith being a Grace that excludes works of any Law, yea, it ſelf as a work; it will aſcribe all to Chriſt and free Grace: It's new Doctrin, that a Command to believe, ſhould be a Command to work for Life, as the obedience to a Law, when it calls Men from under the Law; and it ſaith, That a Believer, is not under the Law, but under Grace: It ſhould have ſaid, you are not under the old Law, but you are under the new Law. You inſtance in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there, doth not denote a priority in time of Faith to Juſtification, but of the end of Faith; we ſhould believe, for this end, that the Grace of Juſtification by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs alone may ſhine into our Hearts, by the light of Faith, that we may have Peace with God in our Conſciences through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo we do not only in our firſt believing, but in all other Acts. And this hinders not but that God's gracious Acts prevent ours and cauſeth them; God's love let forth to us conſtrains us, and is the reaſon of our loving him. Juſtification may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as terminating on our Perſons, and terminating on our Conſciences; in this laſt ſenſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks; but note what is the Antitheſis, And not the Works of a Law. If he had not meant the Works of every Law, he ſhould have diſtinguiſhed, and ſaid, Not by the Works of the old Law, but by the Works of the new Law: It's ſtrange he ſhould keep the <hi>Galatians</hi> in the dark, about the Works of the new Law; it was but Works that they looked for to joyn with Chriſt in Juſtification. I am confident this very diſtinction would have ſatisfied all the Neonomians of his time.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>W.</hi>'s 7th Arg. <hi>The Goſpel is at leaſt part of the Rule by which Chriſt will judge the World; this muſt be a Law if it be a Rule of Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Your Argument is, That Rule, by which God will judge the World, is a Law, but the Goſpel is a Rule by which God will judg the World; therefore, I deny the Minor.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You ſay, Part of that Rule; I pray what's the other part? Will the Rule of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have two parts? Do you mean the old Law will be another part? Or will God judge ſome by the old Law, ſome by the new?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's not likely that God will judge the World by any more than one Law, and that, the Law of Creation, and that by which he governed the World; that Law which hath been the Standard of Righteouſneſs from the beginning of the World to the end.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's likely to be that Law that all the World are become guilty by; they ſhall not be guilty by one Law and judged by another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's likely to be that Law that Men's Conſciences accuſe or excuſe by.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It's likely to be that Law that will reach Jews, Chriſtians, Infidels, and all that never had the written Law or Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If the Goſpel be a Law then, to try by, it muſt ceaſe to be a Goſpel, for it will bring execution of Indignation and Wrath, no good Tidings; I ſuppoſe you will not ſay, the Sentence, <hi>Go ye curſed,</hi> is Goſpel. Well, you ſay,</p>
               <p>The <hi>Work of that day is not to try Chriſt:</hi> No ſure, I believe not; but Chriſt muſt ſit upon his Throne judging the World. <q>Nor whether Chriſt's Righteouſneſs was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to all that Believe; but will be to decide the cauſe of all Men, to ſilence all Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95981:16"/> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> 1. I ſuppoſe you mean to decide Believer's ſtate, which hath been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decided till then. 2. To prove that the reſt of the World had not Faith. As for the firſt ſort, I would know whether their Tryal will be before the Reſurrection or after? Before it can't be, they muſt be raiſed firſt; and thoſe that die in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt. And its ſaid, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſed and happy are they that have part in the firſt Reſurrection;</hi> and how ſhall they be raiſed? Incorruptible, in Glory, like to Chriſt at his Appearance immediately carryed up into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir to meet the Lord. Is it likely that now they are Clothed with all this Glory, at the Reſurrection, they ſhall come to ſtand a Tryal for Juſtification? Surely their ſtate will be fully decided, before Chriſt will raiſe them in this Glory. But you ſay, their Faith muſt come to tryal whether it hath been ſincere; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that will be fully reſolved before the Reſurrection; or how ſhall the Elect be gathered from all Parts? And how ſhall Chriſt diſtinguiſh the Saints from others to raiſe them in Glory?</p>
               <p>But you'l ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, this Tryal will be by the new Law at the Reſurrection of the Unjuſt. 1. Shall they not be raiſed in Diſhonour, with their Conſciences accuſing them by the old Law? 2. How few, in compariſon, will there be of the Millions of wicked that can be juſtified by the new Law that never heard a word of it? 3. Thoſe that have heard of it, never owned it, or were under it; they muſt be tryed by a Law that nature hath brought them under. 4. All their Sins againſt God's Offers and Commands are judged by the old Law; for in the moral Law, God is declared a God that ſhews Mercy unto thouſands. 5. The Offers of Mercy rejected, are but Aggravations of the Sins of thoſe that are condemned already, and make them more inexcuſable. In this ſenſe the Men of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and the Queen of the South, ſhall riſe up in judgment againſt ſome, and condemn them; not that their Actions ſhall be a Law to try by, but that they will be matter of Aggravation to ſuch as had greater means of Grace than they had. Reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Pardon do not bring condemned Perſons to a new Law to Try them by; it leaves them but under the former Law and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>demnation, with a greater Torment upon their Minds and Conſciences. For my part, I look upon your whole Hypotheſis, about the day of Judgment, to be very raw and indigeſted, in that you ſuppoſe it will be like Man's Aſſizes when all Men ſhall be brought to a perſonal Tryal, good and bad, all in mixture, and Believers as well as Unbelievers muſt be Arraigned, and hold up their Hands at the Bar, and ſtand upon their Delivery; whereof ſome upon a formal Tryal ſhall be juſtified, others condemned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I come to ſhew what a Law is, and what Goſpel is.</head>
               <head type="sub">What a Law is.</head>
               <p>The word <hi>Lex</hi> is with ſome <hi>a Ligando,</hi> becauſe it binds to Duty and Obedience; with others it is a <hi>a Legendo,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Quod omnibus ad le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum exponitur pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in ſoro quod diceba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur promulgatio legis. <hi>Iſidor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ariſtot.</p>
                  </note> becauſe among the <hi>Romans,</hi> when a Law was made, it was expoſed publickly, that all might read or know it; and this was called the promulgation of the Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a tribuendo aut diſtribuendo,</hi> becauſe it gives every one its due, by commanding and forbidding, upon a Penalty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt or underſtood. Hence it is not only <hi>regula juſti &amp; injuſti,</hi> (which deſcribes but the preceptive part) but its <hi>regula ſancita</hi> whereby Juſtice doth proceed in a way of diſtribution to juſtify or condemn, and thereby <hi>ſuum cuiquet ribuere,</hi> to give every one his due, if Wages of Sin be due, to pay it; this is the primary and ſtrict ſenſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: in a larger ſenſe it's take for Doctrin, a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom or Uſage, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Inſtituit, docuit, monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it,</hi> &amp;c. and is often uſed for Doctrin or Inſtitution in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> and <hi>Pſalms;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95981:16"/> for the Law of God ſtrictly taken, ſometimes for the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a particular Law or Precept, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.49. Sometimes for the Doctrin of the revealed mind of God in his word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.19. and 119. And ſometimes for a Manner and Cuſtom, as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.19. In which Significations its by the Hebrew di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They have alſo divers other words for particular Statutes, Precepts, Commandments; in treating of which, I ſhall not detain the Reader.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Law in general is an explicit Injunction of Obedience by a rightful Power, with a Penalty annexed. Duty may be owing where its not by any poſitive Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed on Penalty. There are theſe things neceſſary to a Law. 1. That there be a legiſlative Power lodged ſomewhere: That it be Sovereign, whereby the firſt Reaſon of the Law is the good Will and Pleaſure of the Law-giver. 2. That this Sovereign Power be rightfully exerted, or elſe the Law is but an Uſurpation. 3. That the Subject under this Law be capable of performing it, or elſe the Law is tyrannical. 4. If a Promiſe of Reward to Obedience be expreſt or implyed, it becomes a Law-Covenant: But concerning the Nature of that more may be ſaid elſwhere.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In a Law there is but two Parts, the preceptive part and ſanction; which is binding the Subject to Duty, upon the Authority of the Law-giver, and on pain of Curſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced for the Tranſgreſſions thereof. You oft reflect on me for being ignorant of what Sanction is; I muſt tell you, I underſtood <hi>Sancire</hi> before you began to ſtudy, at five Years old, as you ſay you did; and if any one ſpeak of Life and Death diſtinct from the Precept, its you, when you talk of continu ng the Duty and removing the Sanction to another Law; for the removing the Sanction from a Law, is the taking away all the binding Nature of it; and theſe things are inſeparable from a Law with Sanction. 1. Every ſuch Law requires perfect Obedience to the conditional Precepts of whatever kind they be; if the Law require of me a ſmall Matter or a great, it abates not one jot or tittle of what it requires, and my performing that is perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſaid Law. If the King's Law require one ſhilling Poll-Tax of me, eleven pence three Farthings half farthing will not pay my due, nor be accepted. Hence, 2. whereas the Law requires the full Duty without the leaſt Abatement, ſo if I make the leaſt Default of what it requires, I fall under the Curſe of it; and he that is thus by the leaſt Default, whatever his compliance or obedience is beſides, is under a Curſe una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably, the whole Penalty falls upon him. Thus much for a Law in general, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Divine or Human, none allows an imperfect Performance of Conditions required in the ſaid Law, but condemns it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Law of God is a ſtrict Injunction to Man of Obedience to all his revealed Mind, and Will, upon pain of Death. The Original Record of this Law was in Man's Heart, concreated with him; <hi>Adam</hi> had by Nature the things contained in the Law,<note place="margin">Lex <hi>Adamo</hi> data fuit natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis vel p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſitiva, illa in imagine D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i involvebatur &amp; in corde ſcripta, <hi>Rom. 2.14, 15.</hi> Lex poſitiva conſiſtebat i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one arboris ſcientiae boni &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, <hi>Gen. 2.17. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i.</hi>
                  </note> a few dark Remains whereof continue in fallen Man in his ſinful Condition: This not only comprehended thoſe Precepts which the Jews call the Law of Nature, which are <hi>Eadem apud omnes homines in omni tempore &amp; omni loco. Which are the ſame among all Men, and in every Place:</hi> But it requires exact Obedience to any particular, or more peculiar Precepts that God afterward ſhould require Obedience by, of any one Perſon, or ſort of People, even God's extraordinary Commands ſuch as to <hi>Abraham</hi> of offering up his Son. Again, it doth not bind only to the external Acts of Obedience but to the internall, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple from whence it flows, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.21, 27. c. 22.37, 38, 39. This Principle and internal heart Conformity Man had at the firſt; <q>All Preſcription of Duty belongs to the Law, as <hi>Voet. diſput. tom.</hi> 4. 24. And this we muſt hold, if with all the Reformed we will maintain the Law's Perfection, as containing in its compaſs all Vertues and Duties of Holineſs.</q> 
                  <hi>Witſ.</hi> 197. <hi>de foed.</hi> Hence whatever is a Tranſgreſſion of ours in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Obedience to any of God's Precepts, that were or ſhould be given, the very
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95981:17"/> leaſt, though but in a defect of Faith or Love to God in the Heart, is condemned by God's Law: Will any Man ſay that God hath commanded Faith and Repentance at any Time to Man, and that was not implyed in the Law at firſt given to Man, doth not that Law condemn every Diſobedience, Impenitency and Unbelief<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if it condemns the Sins it commands the Duties. The Law of Creation condemned all Sin, which could not be but by the Fall, and hence commanded all contrary Duty, and therefore Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in caſe of Sin.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Law was twice ſolemnly promulgated, 1. To <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradice,</hi> in which Promulgation God did bring him upon the tryal of his Obedience in one particular Precept or Prohibition, as a part of his Revealed Mind and Will; and likewiſe declared the Penalty of the Breach of the whole Law in that ſin. 2. On Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> which Law was but a recognizing and tranſcript of the ſaid Original Law, writ in Man's Heart, but ſo as to be expreſſive of the fallen ſtate of Man; in which Law, though but a brief Summary in ten Heads what was that moral Obedience God at firſt required of Man, yet therein its abundantly declared, That Man by a moral Obligation was bound to obſerve whatever God enjoyned as a Duty to Sinners in Faith and Repentance, and in all Matters of inſtituted Worſhip under the Old or New Teſtament, in the firſt Table, and moſt eſpecially in the firſt and ſecond Commandments: Though thoſe particular Commands as to the Moſaical Inſtitution were alterable, yet they being the revealed Mind and Will of God, for the time being, Men lay under a moral Obligation as the Principle and Foundation of that Obedience. So where-ever God commands and requires any Duty in the Goſpel, the Law primarily obligeth us to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>De comminationibus ſi quae ſunt in foedere pratiae videamus, ſi ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate rem putare v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>limus,</hi> &amp;c</p>
                     <p>Though the Goſpel ſeems to have Comminations in it, yet if we accurately conſider the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Covenant of Grace hath no peculiar Comminations; all Comminations or Threats belong to the Law; which Law, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to all its Parts doth accommodate, and ſuits itſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lf to the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Witſ. de foed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> and will revenge all Diſobedience and Imperfection, if we are not ſecured from its Curſe in ſome way of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Satisfaction and Obedience; there needs no other Law with Sanction to try and execute a Tranſgreſſor by: This is the Law by which all the World becomes guilty before God; by which he governeth the World, condemns every Sin in the very regenerate, and every impenitent Unbeliever; and by this Law, and it only Chriſt will judge the World. Neither doth the greatneſs and Aggravation of any Sin, remove it to the tryal of another Law, as in refuſal of Goſpel Remedy, but leaves Men the more inexcuſable under a higher degree of puniſhment inflicted by the ſame Law: And whereas that Place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to prove the Change of the Law-Sanction, and that it is not the Law of Nature but the Law of the Goſpel by which Chriſt will judge the World: The allegation is grounded on a manifeſt Miſtake, for mark what is ſaid, v. 16. In its next coherence it belongs to v. 12. (for v. 13, 14, 15. are ſhut in by a Parentheſis) and then the ſenſe is plainly thus, <hi>as many as have ſinned in the Law ſhall be judged by the Law, in the day when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of Men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpel,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> according as I have preached, That Chriſt ſhall judge the World by the Law; for he ſaith two ſorts of Men ſhall be judged by the Law, ſuch as had never no Law, but what was written in their Hearts, and ſuch as had the written Law; and Chriſt ſhall judge them both, according to the Truth of the Goſpel which he had preached, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. and this is according to the account Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> gives of the Text.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Hence the <hi>Law</hi> of God is but one from firſt to laſt, indeed in this one Law there are many Precepts, ten in the Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> Law, and thoſe ten contain multitudes of Duties in other places of Scripture more particularly expreſſed: And upon this Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Obedience is built all the Ceremonial Laws and Judicial, which had but a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Sanction; and no more hath the inſtituted Goſpel worſhip, and are but Branches that fall off, but our Obedience to them for their time is Moral, becauſe they are the Command of God, and that Moral Duty to conform to the revealed Mind and Will of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95981:17"/> and will be our Glory in Heaven, though particular Circumſtances and Actions wherein this Obedience is now ordinarily expreſt, will ceaſe: Hence it was not needful that Chriſt ſhould exert his perfect Obedience in thoſe Circumſtances and Actions which do attend all the Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of States, Stations and Relations that we are in,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, The Law is the whole Rule of Obedience which God gave to the Church under the Old Teſtament. It was a perfect and complea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rule of Obedience, which God required of his Church, the moral Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Foundation of the whole both Ceremonial and Judaical. By vertue of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> it was accompanied with a Power and Efficacy enab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing unto Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Law ln it ſelf as meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preceptive and commanding, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred no Power and Ability unto thoſe that were under its Authority, no more do the meer Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nds of the Goſpel. Under the O. Teſtament, it enforced Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from the ſeverity of its ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion. D.<hi>O.</hi> of Juſt. p. 4 13, 144.</note> neither would it have been eſſential to <hi>Adam</hi>'s perfection if he had ſtood, nor will it be to glorified Saints. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Law of God is perpetual, and its an eternal Truth, <hi>do and live,</hi> as that the Soul that Sins ſhall dye, Not one jot or Tittle of the Law ſhall paſs away till all be accompliſhed, Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away firſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.18. not that it is vacated when fulfilled, but eſtabliſhed: And our Saviour tells us, <hi>That he that will break one of the leaſt of theſe Commandments, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called the leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven;</hi> What muſt they then be called, who tell us, God hath vacated this Holy, Righteous and Good Law, and brought in another in the room of it that diſpenſeth with little Sins, and makes them not of a damning Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Concerning the GOSPEL:</head>
               <head type="sub">What Goſpel is.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Engliſh Word <hi>Goſpel</hi> comes from <hi>Good, God,</hi> or <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>Spell,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a Word or Saying, ſo that Goſpel is as much as a Good Word, a comfortable Word or Saying of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Word comes of</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> bene, <hi>and</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> nuntius, &amp; eſt laetum vel foelix Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> or the Spirit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the proper Signification of it is a good Meſſage, or joyful News; and ſo its uſed by <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> and <hi>Appian,</hi> and in that Senſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is uſed <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.10, 11. The LXXII. uſe it expreſly for good Tidings, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.10. and ſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.7. <hi>The Goſpel that we are to believe as the Glad Tidings of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mar. 1.15. Luk. 2.10. <hi>The Publication of Chriſt's Doctrine,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.15. Rom. 1.1. <hi>The Goſpel of Ages or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Goſpel,</hi> Rev. 14.6. I know no place that it is uſed otherwiſe than for acceptable News, and glad Tidings, and no where in the Senſe of a Law or Law-Covenant; and it can be no otherwiſe, becauſe to whom are theſe glad Tidings brought, but to poor Sinners, that are fallen under the Law, become guilty before God, utterly hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and helpleſs in themſelves? and by the ſaid Law, or any Law that requires the leaſt degree of Holineſs as a federal Condition of Life and Salvation. Chriſt himſelf <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1. tells us who he came to preach Goſpel good Tidings to, it was to the poor, broken-hearted, Captives, Blind, Impriſoned. The Hebrew Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of the ſame ſignification, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chald. and Syr. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now then the Goſpel is the Manifeſtation of the Grace of the Covenant, the good News and glad Tidings of Life and Salvation, promiſed in the Covenant of Grace to Tranſgreſſors of the Law, that lye under the Curſe of it, and was promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated immediately after the Fall (before the Sentence was paſſed) by way of Promiſe, without the leaſt mention of a New Law or Law Conditions to be performed by Man to inveſt him in the ſaid Promiſe: The Promiſe was to Chriſt and of Chriſt, That he ſhould deſtroy the Work of the Devil, and ſpoil Principalities and Powers, and give Life to to the World, that the Devil by his Subtilty and Malice had plotted to deſtroy; and as he thought had effected the total Ruine and Deſtruction of. The like Promiſe was to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95981:18"/> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> 430 Years before the Law. The manner of this Salvation was ſoon exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in Sacrifices, in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Family, as Types of Chriſt the great Sacrifice for Sin; they were continued in the Families of the Faithful both before and after the Flood, and in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s and the Patriarchs till the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was erected and organized in the Wilderneſs, when the whole Ceremonial Service was eſtabliſhed, the OEconomy whereof was but an entire Type of Chriſt and the Goſpel in the Tabernacle and Temple, ſtate of the Church; ſo that the whole Service was no more than their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, wherein Chriſt was daily preached to them: Which Goſpel of theirs laboured under much faultineſs, comparatively to what it was afterward at the Appearance, and by the Miniſtry of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. compared with <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5, 6.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Goſpel brings Life and Immortality to Light by the Promiſe, which was not ſo clearly diſcovered before Chriſt's Incarnation and Miniſtry, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5. He appears to be the great Sacrifice ſo long fore-typified, as likewiſe the great Prieſt that was to come, <hi>after the Order of Melchiſedeck,</hi> and the great Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> propheſied of: To him gave all the Prophets Witneſs, and <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> pointed him out, As the <hi>Lamb of God that took away the Sins of the World;</hi> and that he had <hi>received the Spirit without Meaſure.</hi> The Hiſtory of Chriſt's Life, Doctrine, Death and Exaltation are eminent Proofs of theſe glad Tydings, from whence the four Evangeliſts are rightly named. The Witneſs and Miniſtry of the Apoſtles contain likewiſe the ſame, whereby there is the giving the Knowledg of Salvation, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. and that through this Knowledg we ſhould have all things pertaining to Life and Godlineſs, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Promiſe of the Goſpel to us, contains all good News, being free and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute to Sinners (ſuch 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11. ch. 2.25.) of Chriſt and of Eternal Life and Salvation in him. 2. Promiſes of the firſt Grace freely and graciouſly beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on us as of Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. the Spirit, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.12, 13. the new Creation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. and free Juſtification, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. the new Heart, 26. a Promiſe to make us to walk in his ways, and that we ſhall be his People, <hi>ibid.</hi> a Promiſe to be taught of God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.45. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13. Yea the bringing us into a true Goſpel Obedience to the Law, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. the making Chriſt our Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs and Sanctification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> whereby Obedience to God's Law is graciouſly given us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.29. the promiſe of Perſeverance, that we ſhall not depart from God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Promiſes made to Chriſt, and of Chriſt, wherein our abſolute Salvation is wrapped up, ſo as to be a Covenant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. c. 49.6. c. 53.11, 12. Promiſes to him of the Throne and Dominion of <hi>David,</hi> in a ſpiritual Senſe, ſuch as concern his prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and prophetical Offices, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 10. To inſtance in all would be long.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All the Names of Chriſt, as Meſſias, Jeſus, Emanuel; the account of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of his Offices, of his Office in general, Mediator, Redeemer, Saviour; of Chriſt in particular, of his Prophetick, Prieſtly, Kingly Offices; his exerciſe of them, and his excellent Spirit which he ſhewed therein, full of Meekneſs, Compaſſion, Wiſdom and Zeal. All this is Goſpel, and good News to Sinners.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The gracious free Invitations that are made to Sinners, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. lat. 2 Cor. 5.1. with Promiſes for Encouragement. Here's high and rich Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Promiſe of Principle and Strength to perform every Duty required; of his Spirit, to work in us to will and do; of God's Love ſhed abroad in our Hearts to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us, of life itſelf; and that he will be the Reſurrection and Life; of Love, ſpringing from the Love of God; of making us good Trees, that we may bring forth good Fruit, is all wonderful Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All the Diſcoveries Chriſt hath made of his Father; his eternal Election, his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting with him in a Covenant-way, ſhewing us the Myſtery of the Father, revealing him, by his glorious Deſigns to glorifie his Juſtice and Mercy in ſuch a way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; his Deſigns to magnify his Law, and make it honourable; to exalt his Son Jeſus to be a Prince and Saviour, and give Remiſſion of Sins; to exalt his free Grace in this ſalvation by a free juſtification, adoption, ſanctification, and glory; and in doing this, Juſtice ſhould loſe nothing of its due, is all great and glorious Goſpels.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:95981:18"/>8. That in all theſe great and precious things, there is ſuch a connexion together that one encourageth and leadeth to another, Promiſe leads to Duty, and Duty to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Promiſes, Grace leads to Glory, and that Perſeverance is as infallibly ſetled in electing Grace, and as abſolutely as the firſt Grace. This is admirable Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The great and clear diſcoveries that are made of the evil of ſin, of the dangers ſin leads to, and ſinners are in and running into, by continuing in ſin, and laying open the ſtrict nature of the Law, that it diſpenſeth not with the leaſt ſin, it requires ſtill perfect righteouſneſs and holineſs, and ſentenceth the ſinner to eternal death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for it; and therefore it's impoſſible, that any fleſh living, by ordinary deſcent from <hi>Adam,</hi> can be juſtified by the Works of the Law; it's a gracious and neceſſary piece of Goſpel to take off a poor ſinner from the love of ſin and fondneſs of his own righteouſneſs, which every ſinner by nature is apt unto, and to ſet up the Lord Jeſus as the only Name whereby he can be ſaved, and to ſhew, that he is able and willing to ſave to the uttermoſt, whereby a ſinner becomes dead to the Law, and married by faith unto Jeſus Chriſt. This is in the glorious Goſpel of God and our Saviour: It is the light of it that ſhines into the heart doth this.</p>
               <p n="10">10. It is good News and glad Tydings, that the grace of God in the Goſpel doth not make void the Law, but eſtabliſheth it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. Neither is the Law againſt the Promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. tho' that he that is under a Law for juſtification, is under a Curſe, and that by the oeconomy of the grace of Chriſt in the New Covenant, the Law and Goſpel do ſweetly harmonize: 1. In that the Law hath been fulfilled in Chriſt as to all righteouſneſs, it hath a full Sanction as to every believer in the active and paſſive obedience of Chriſt; their delivery from the curſe of it being by this, that he was made a curſe for them; all their ſins are condemned in his fleſh, he bearing them on the Croſs; the Law hath its end as to all righteouſneſs and compleat perfect holineſs in Chriſt; believers are all compleat and perfect in Chriſt as to the Law. 2. It's good News, that Chriſt's death was not only the ſatisfying of the Law and Juſtice of God on the account of our ſins, and, together with his active obedience, the merit of grace and glory; but that this ſame death of Chriſt was the Sanction and Ratification of all the Grace of the New Covenant, as a Teſtament, being by the death of the Teſtator, and as a Law to Chriſt, which he lay under by his Father's injunction to perform. And this is the Sanction ſpoken of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 8.6. and more fully explained, <hi>c.</hi> 9.15 16, 17. compared with <hi>c.</hi> 10.7. 3. It's good News to a believer, that God hath provided a way for him to come into an acceptable obedience through Jeſus Chriſt, to the Law of God,<note place="margin">Lex attemperata foederi gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae &amp; juxta illud inſcripta cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di electorum jubet ea omnia quae in Evangelio proponuntur, fide non ficta amplecti &amp; conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter iſti gratiae &amp; gloriae Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſuam inſti tuere. Quando ergo Deus in foedere gratiae promittit p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccatori electo fidem Reſcipiſcientiam &amp; conſequenter vitam aeternam, tum Lex cujus obligatio nunquam poteſt ſolvi quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad omne officium ſeſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit obſtringit hominem ut il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li veritati aſſentiatur, promiſſa illa bona magnifaciat, Impenſe deſideret, quaerat, amplectatur. <hi>Witſ. de Foed. p. 198.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe the Grace of the Goſpel cauſeth him to love the Law and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt in the Goſpel-way of performance. He ſaith, <hi>Oh how do I love thy law; Oh that my ways were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to keep thy ſtatutes;</hi> and he deſires, that now God would grant him his Law graciouſly: ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. For the grace of God in the Goſpel writes the Law in his heart in a true love to God with all his heart, and a love to the Law of God, to the holineſs, juſtice and goodneſs of it, and his great deſire is now, that in Chriſt Jeſus, and conformity to him, God's Law may be honoured, and therefore he looks upon the very performance of holy Duties accordingly, as his benefit and priviledge by the grace of the Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt is ſanctification to him, he is created in Chriſt Jeſus to good works, he is redeemed from all iniquity, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12, 13. and taught by the grace of God to deny all ungodly and worldly luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from love and thankfulneſs to Chriſt to keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and this New Goſpel reſtored Principle of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95981:19"/> is the New Commandment ſpoken of <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.34. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.7, 8. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. not that it was materially a New Command. 4. Laſtly, It is great and good Tydings, that Jeſus Chriſt is ſet on the Holy Hill of <hi>Zion;</hi> that he is King, Head and Governour to his Church; and that he hath provided particular right Laws, Rules and Precepts for them to walk by, according to the original deſign, purity and intention of God's Law; and that now the Law of God goes no longer out of Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> but out of Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and the Word of the Lord from the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem, Iſa.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18, 22, 23. And it's Goſpel, that all Power is not only given to Chriſt in his Church as King thereof, but all Power in Heaven and Earth is committed to him, as to governing Providence, and that he ſhall judge the World at the laſt day. Theſe things are all the good Tydings of the Goſpel, ratified in the Covenant of Grace, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, freely and fully beſtowed on us in the Goſpel, and upon no federal condition of our own performance, either before or after converſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="arguments">
               <head>Arguments that the Goſpel is not a New Law with Sanction.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If Law and Goſpel are ſpecifically diſtinct, then the Goſpel is not a Law, nor the Law a Goſpel, but Law and Goſpel are ſpecifically diſtinct, therefore the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is not a Law. The conſequence of the Major is undeniable to any one that underſtands the nature of Genus and Species. The revealed offers of ſalvation were never but by two ways to Man, by <hi>Works</hi> and by <hi>Grace,</hi> that is called Law, this Goſpel, and they are <hi>contra</hi> diſtinct, <hi>ſub proximo genere,</hi> and <hi>adverſa,</hi> as much as <hi>homo &amp; brutum ſub animali;</hi> and the Law can no more be called Goſpel, or the Goſpel a Law, than a Man may be called a Brute, or a Brute a Man.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Law and Goſpel-grace are oppoſed expreſly by the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. <hi>The law was given by Moſes, but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Here is not a Law and a Law oppoſed,<note place="margin">Evangelium non eſſe legem, ſed ab ea plurimum diſtinctum tum ipſa arguit appellatio quam ponderat, <hi>Theophyl. in Praef. Matth. &amp; Euſeb. l. 1. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione Evang. c. 1.</hi> Tum manifeſta Antitheſis quae eſt, <hi>Joh. 1.17. Rom. 10.5, 6.</hi> Tum utriuſque diſcrimen ſitum in patefactionis ordine natura, promulgatione, miniſterio in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſeu differentia promiſſionum in effectis, adjunctis efficacia, officio utriuſque in applicatione ad objecta: tum conſtitutus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae purioris conſenſus quae ſemper Evangelium a lege diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crevit quemadmodum, <hi>Cyril. Alex.</hi>
                  </note> but a Law and Grace eſſentially differing; for an old Law and a new do not differ eſſentially, but <hi>ſecundum adjuncta</hi> only, in the like manner and for the ſame end; Chriſt and <hi>Moſes</hi> are oppoſed, Chriſt as a Son, to <hi>Moſes</hi> as a Servant, one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Miniſter of the Law, the other of the free grace of the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.5, 6. As Mediators, one of a legal adminiſtration, that vailed the grace of the Goſpel; Chriſt ſuch a Mediator of the New Teſtament, who brought life and immortality to light through the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10 Upon the account of this ſpecifick diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Law and Goſpel, it is that Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> and Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is above, the heavenly are oppoſed to the earthly in that Spiritual Allegory of <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> applied <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25. which oppoſition between theſe Mounts is fully and admirably managed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18, 22. To this let me add the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick difference that is made between thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one and under the other, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. There are ſome under the Law, and ſome under grace; he ſaith not ſome under an old Law, ſome under a new; but what's the condition of them under the Law? ſin reigns unto death; but as to thoſe under Grace, grace reigneth through righteouſneſs [<hi>i. e.</hi> of Chriſt, not of works of our obedience to any Law] unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life. Laſtly, The oppoſition made between the Works of the Law and the Grace of the Goſpel, is in the point of juſtification; the Works of the Law, or any Law, are peremptorily rejected by the Apoſtle in the point of juſtification; ſo that if Grace ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in a way of Works, Grace and Works here could not be oppoſed: See thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95981:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> two famous places that peremptorily reject all Works of what kind ſoever, of what Law ſoever, from Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. where its ſaid by the Works of a Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. no Fleſh living ſhall be juſtified: It is reaſonable to think, that if the Apoſtle had intended we ſhould be juſtified by any Law,<note place="margin">Alexand. in <hi>c. 40.</hi> Iſa. Hieron. <hi>l. 1.</hi> Contra Pelagianos &amp; plurimorum ubi opus adduci poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt teſtimonia. <hi>Chriſtop. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largi Jeſuitiſmu, p. 71. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſ. An. D. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</hi>
                  </note> that he would not have told us by what Law-Works? Would he have ſpoken ſo univerſally of all Law-Works? Are not all good Works, towards God and Man, commanded in the Law? But are ſome Works of one Law and ſome of another? This Remark of mine, obout leaving out the prepoſitive Article, ſhewing that the Words of all Laws are indefinitely here meant, you would blow away as a Cobweb: Your words are, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſuch Cobwebs, in the face of the plain ſcope of the Bible, doth this Cauſe ſtand.</hi> Cobwebs are fit enough to catch Flies in; but I never fear an Adverſary that ſpits at Arguments inſtead of anſwering them. Where's the Argument, you ſay, becauſe in a few places the Article ὼ is not put in? [You ſhould have ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.] <q>Therefore the Apoſtle excludes every ſort, when he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excludes only one ſort, as appears by the whole Context; nay, when at the ſame time ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Species under that general, <hi>Rom. 3.27.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Therefore Ver. 20. We have the general of all Laws, there's no Juſtification by the Works of a Law; and know you not that which is denyed to the Genus as ſuch, is denyed to the Species; and tho' he mentions a Law of Faith, <hi>v.</hi> 27. in the ſenſe or ſenſes which have been above mentioned, yet it is manifeſt that he abſolutely denies Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification to Faith as a Law-Work; for elſe, why had he not excepted Faith as a Law-Work, when he excludes all Works? And when he ſheweth all Works are excluded, he ſaith, where is boaſting then? Saith he, it is excluded by the Nature and Power of true Faith, which will always lay the Creature low, and exclude all matter of Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that may be in us; he ſaith not, we are juſtified by Faith as a Work of the new Law; but ſaith, that Faith ſtands up againſt all ſuch Works, and Law-Juſtification; and this is witneſſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the Law and the Prophets, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Miniſtry, as well as the Prophets, were the prepoſitive Points at Law, in a peculiar ſenſe; but what is it that's witneſſed? It's that the Righteouſneſs of God is manifeſted, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without a Law, any Law for Juſtification by Goſpel grace. You miſtake if you apprehend we make this our great Argument, to prove that the Goſpel in its nature is not a Law with Sanction; it is the plain ſcope and deſign of the Apoſtle, in all thoſe places where he diſputes againſt Juſtification by Works, that we argue from, and make uſe of this obſervation, as a corroborating Argument, that his plain intent is to exclude, not only the Works of the moral Law, but the Works of any Law; for the Apoſtle deals with the <hi>Galatians,</hi> which hankered after Circumciſion, and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of obſervation of ſome of the Moſaical Ceremonies, would have introduced the Works of the Law to ſhare in the Matter of their Righteouſneſs: And, therefore, by uſing Law in the largeſt and moſt comprehenſive ſenſe, he caſts out all-Law Works as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Juſtification; and this is the ſenſe Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> hath of the Apoſtle's Scope on <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <q>St. <hi>Paul</hi> having proved the World to be guilty before God, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Wrath, he concludes that which he undertakes to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> That no Man could be juſtified by the Works of any Law; for having diſproved one part of the disjunct Propoſition, he eſtabliſheth the other, <hi>viz.</hi> Seeing we are not juſtified by a Law; therefore, only by Faith in Chriſt alone, Chriſt apprehended by Faith, as the Goſpel teacheth that we are both juſtified and ſaved; therefore, that the Goſpel is the power of God unto Salvation to every Believer; which was the ſtate of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as laid down in the beginning of the Epiſtle. He tells us what doth further ſhew or demonſtrate theſe things duly conſidered; that in this Verſe, by the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law without an Article, all Doctrin is underſtood, whether Written or not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which doth command or forbid any thing, as the ſeries of his Arguments, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95981:20"/> effect which he aſcribes to the Law, in diſcovering Sin doth prove; you may ſee much more in him to this purpoſe: The Works of the Law are called the doing of thoſe things,<note place="margin">Haec autem diligenter conſiderata manifeſta indicant in hoc ver ſiculo, appellatione legis ſine Articulo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligi omnem doctrinam ſcriptam aut non ſcriptam, quae aliquid aut jubeat aut interdicat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> which the Law commands, as they are done by us, or not done by us, not as ſimply commanded by the Law.</q> Now I ſuppoſe you will not call this learned Man's arguing here a Cobweb. It were eaſie to ſhew upon what probable Reaſons the Prepoſitive is added or omitted, in other places of the Epiſtles where Law is mentioned, which to avoid prolixity I muſt now omit. It's enough at preſent that it is left out in theſe eminent places, where Juſtification by any Works of any Law, is utterly denyed and condemned. It's frivolouſly objected by you, that the omiſſion of the Article here, argues not; <q>becauſe the Socinians would improve the leaving out of ὸ, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. againſt the Deity of Chriſt; and ſay the word was a God, not the God; a God by office, (as one preached at <hi>P. H.</hi>) whereas its in that Text an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, and there is doubtleſs a great force in it; for as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith by the firſt words, the word was in the beginning, the eternal Eſſence of the Son is aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</q> 2. By the next, The Word was with God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (where the Article is expreſt, and the Perſon of the Son is diſtinguiſhed from the Perſon of the Father, God without ſeparation. And in the third Enunciation, he affirms, That the Word was, (<hi>i. e.</hi> ver. 1. <hi>Et eſſentialiter Deus) Patri,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntially God, the ſame in Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with the Father; and if the Article had been added, and it had been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it had affirmed the Son to be the ſame Perſon with the Father. It's no ſmall matter, therefore, in the declaring this divine Myſtery, that the Article is firſt added, and then afterwards omitted, to ſhew Chriſt is God, tho' not God the Father. See what an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument yours is, becauſe the Socinians will make a falſe Inference from the leaving out ὸ, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. Therefore it muſt be Socianiſm to argue from <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. becauſe the Prepoſitive is left out, and Law uſed indefinitely, that all Laws are underſtood, and Juſtification by all Law-Works are excluded. And whereas, you ſay, the Text ſpeaks directly of the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> if you mean thereby the moral Law, it was eſſentially the ſame with the Law of Innocency; and the denial of Juſtification by one, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a denial of Juſtification by the other; and ſo by all Doctrins, requiring duty, as Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith. What you ſay of <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11. militates againſt your ſelf, whereas you ſay, <hi>Was every Law given</hi> 430 <hi>years after Abraham? Is not the Apoſtle expreſs, in the</hi> 3 <hi>firſt Chapters, that that Law was the Jewiſh Law?</hi> [Do you not mean Moral and Ceremonial, and Judicial? For of theſe parts were the Jewiſh Law] <hi>or at moſt the Law of Nature together with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> Were not theſe all Laws of Duty that God made, and all comprehended in the Law of Nature, requiring univerſal obedience to God in all things, that he ſhould ever Command?</p>
               <p>But obſerve that Juſtification by Chriſt, which is the ſame always in the Apoſtle's ſenſe as Juſtification by Faith, is oppoſed to Juſtification by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was the way the Jews looked after, partly by Sacrifice, partly by their Obedience to that Law in the preceptive part; and thus they followed after that Law of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31. and attained it not, becauſe they ſought it not by Faith, <hi>ſed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>quaſi operibus legis,</hi> as it were by the Works of the Law, <hi>v.</hi> 32. Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> refuting <hi>Eraſmus</hi> on that place, ſaith, <q>
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> wrongs the Jews, in that he thinks that they lookt upon the Salvation they had, to have been by Works only, the Grace of God excluded; for the contrary to this Aſſertion appears by the Prayer of the Phariſee, that the Jews had no other Opinion of Merits and Grace, than now our Sophiſts have, which conjoyn Free-will with Grace, and Faith with Works. And indeed this was the Stumbling-block. I might go through <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles to evince this, That all ſorts of Works are oppoſed to Grace in Juſtification, <hi>quaſi e regione perpetuo adverſantur.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:95981:20"/> And this is the Point he deals ſo roundly with the <hi>Galatians</hi> about, <hi>viz.</hi> Their Judaizing, in joyning Works with Faith in Juſtification; not ſo much the Ceremony of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which at another time he admitted of, but becauſe of the reaſon why now the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians</hi> thought Circumciſion ſo neceſſary, <hi>viz.</hi> as a Work of the Law; therefore he teſtified, That if they were circumciſed, Chriſt would profit them nothing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they were obliged to keep the whole Law for Juſtification; becauſe obeying it in one point would not ſerve, they could not be juſtified partly by Chriſt, and partly by ſome partial obedience to the Law; and there was as much reaſon to plead for a <hi>Moſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> imperfect obedience, to joyn with the Sacrifices in Juſtification, before Chriſt, as there is now for an Evangelical imperfect obedience to conjoyn with Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs now, and more.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Grace and Free-gifts is by all Men oppoſed to all conditional claim, upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of a Duty required by any Law; and the Apoſtle always makes this Debt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. Let the conditional part be never ſo ſmall, it's a Debt <hi>ex pacto.</hi> Hence the Apoſtle placeth both eternal Life and the Righteouſneſs by which we are juſtified, all in free Gift to us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15, 16, 22. Yea he directly oppoſeth the Goſpel gift of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life (which comprehends Grace and Glory) to any Law with Sanction, <hi>v.</hi> laſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> any Law that pays Death as the Wages of Sin; <hi>The Wages of Sin is Death, but the gift of God is eternal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ife through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Now if your new Law makes Death the Wages of any Sin, then the Goſpel gift of eternal Life is oppoſed to it.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 25. "The Benefits are not given us for our Faith, but upon believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> For and Upon, in a Covenant ſenſe, are the the ſame; to convey an Eſtate upon the payment of 5 Shillings is a Bargain, and good <hi>ex pacto,</hi> tho' the Eſtate be worth hundreds. You ſay, <q>If a Man ſays, I will give you a thouſand Pound, provided you will come and fetch it; is it not free Gift?</q> I ſuppoſe its reckoned ſo by him that is able and willing to fetch it. But the Caſe may be ſo, that if ſome Men offer me a thouſand Pound, I will not fetch it to have it, and then I may not be able. One may offer a thouſand Pound to a Man that lies with broken Arms and Legs in the bottom of a deep Well, provided he will come and fetch it, eſpecially when he knows no Body can ſet his Limbs and help him out. And how oft do you ſay the firſt Grace is ablolute? And to ſay the ſame thing is abſolute in the power of another, and make it a condition by Law with Sanction unto me, is the greateſt abſurdity in the World. And I tell you, that if a rich Man offers a hundred Pound to a poor Man, Lame and Blind, and in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the King makes a Law he ſhould come and fetch it, or elſe be hang'd, it would ceaſe to be a Free-gift.</p>
               <p n="2">Arg. 2. <hi>That which is a Law with Sanction curſeth every one under that Law, with an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrievable Curſe upon the firſt Tranſgreſſion of the ſaid Law; but the Goſpel doth not bind any one under a Curſe irretrievable, by the Goſpel, upon the firſt Sin, or many Sins committed againſt the Grace of it;</hi> therefore the Goſpel is not a Law with Sanction.</p>
               <p>The Major is very manifeſt, That there's no Law pardons a Tranſgreſſion of itſelf: It is a univerſal Maxim concerning not only the Law of Creation, but of all Laws, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He that is under Law is under a Curſe, provided he doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all things that are written in the Book of the ſaid Law that he is under:</hi> therefore firſt he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. in the ſecond place, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you ſpeak of your New Law, the Condition whereof you make Faith and ſincere Obedience; lowered Conditions and imperfect Obedience: And theſe are the <hi>all things</hi> contained in the Book of this Law; then immediately upon the Publiſhing and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation thereof all Unbelievers are irretrievably condemned by that Law. The Wages due by that Law to every Unbeliever, upon his firſt unbelief<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is Death: And the ſaid Law cannot relieve him, becauſe he hath not done whatever was writ in the Book of this Law; its true one Law may relieve us in reſpect of another, in ſome ſenſe at leaſt as to the Curſe of it, but no Law relieves from its own Curſe, therefore if the new
<pb facs="tcp:95981:21"/> Law curſeth Unbelief, it curſeth the Unbeliev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> irr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>treivably, upon the firſt Act of Sin in that kind.</p>
               <p>The Minor is plain, becauſe the Goſpel do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reliev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Curſe that lies upon Men for Unbelief (being in its proper Natu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Tranſg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſion of, and Diſobedience to the firſt Law) there's no Sin or Curſe but th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f, though aggravated by the rejection of a Remedy; all Laws with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, give the due Recompence (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by that Law) to the Tranſgreſſor of it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny one Point, therefore ſin is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, in reſpect of that Law againſt which it is, unpardon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble, for therein the nature of that Sin is adjuſted, and the Puniſhment that is made due to it. Hence therefore if the Goſpel be a Law with Sanction, every one that appears upon Tryal to have tranſgreſſed it after its Promulgation, leſs or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is under the Curſe of it, and that Perſon which any Law hath once curſed, it can never bleſs; therefore this Poſition puts thouſands under a moſt certain, hopeleſs and helpleſs Condition by the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. That which is a Law with Sanction, if it contain a Promiſe of Benefits upon Obedience, is a Covenant of Works; for up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the ſame Grounds that the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is the Wages due in caſe of diſobedience: Upon the ſame is the Benefit due, in caſe of Obedience; the ſame Law make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bt as well as the other, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is of Law is of Debt, either upon the account of Sin or of Righteouſneſs; the Law was the ſame upon both accounts to <hi>Adam,</hi> Life had been a Reward, and Wages due as well as Death: Therefore the Apoſtle argues ſo ſtrenuouſly againſt all kind of Works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to him that worketh there's a Reward; not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not of Grace bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bt; and he excepteth not him that worketh according to the new, but to him that worketh, whether according to the Old or New Law; the Reward to him that worketh by any Law, is Debt by the ſaid Law.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If the Goſpel be a Law, its either the ſame Law with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Law of Nature, or a diſtinct Law from it: But its neither the ſame Law nor a diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct Law from it, therefore no Law with Sanction. The Neceſſity of the Conſequence in the disjunction cannot be doubted by any Man of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>The Minor is thus demonſtrated. 1. Its not the ſame Law with the Law of Nature; this you will not ſay, becauſe you call it a New Law: And if it be the ſame Law, then you have no Pretence to evade all the Conſequences that will be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>awn upon you from the Doctrine and Arguments of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> therefore I doubt not but I am ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of you as to this part of the Dilemma.</p>
               <p>Therefore I come to the ſecond, That which muſt be eſſentially the ſame Law with the Old Law, is not a diſtinct Law from it, but your New Law muſt be eſſentially the ſame with the Old Law, therefore is not diſtinct from it.</p>
               <p>Your new Law can have no Eſſentials diſtinct from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Old Law, for if it have the ſame Eſſentials its the ſame, the ſame Matter and Form, and the ſame integral Parts wherein they conſiſt. The parts of a Law are Condition and Promiſe, in caſe of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and Threat in caſe of Diſobedience, the connexion of theſe makes the Form; all this you'll allow. Hence there's the ſame Law-Nature in one as in the other, and therefore its a Law in the ſame way and manner, and a Man under it muſt be dealt with in a Law way and manner: Obedience to God was commanded there, and ſo here; Diſobedience to God forbidden there, and ſo here; Life promiſed there upon Obedience, and Death threatned there upon Diſobedience, and ſo here: And what Obedience is there which is not commanded in the Old Law? And what Diſobedience that is not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den there? But you will ſay the Old Law commanded perfect Obedience, and the new imperfect. <hi>A.</hi> The New Law would not certainly command what the Old Law forbad; but the Old Law forbad all Imperfection in Obedience, and curſed it. 2. Whatever the degree of Obedience is that any Law requires, its perfect, in regard of that Law that requires it. 3. It ſhould be ſtrange if God ſhould make that which is imperfect, ſinful, condemned Obedience by one Law, to be perfect Obedience, and juſtifying by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95981:21"/> a New, and ſo ſet Law againſt Law. Laſtly, as to the Promiſe, its the ſame, for it was everlaſting Life, both in the old Covenant and the new; the manner of having it by Works or by Grace, alters not the nature of the thing itſelf. A Houſe in itſelf is the ſame whether I purchaſe it or it be given. From all which I conclude, This pretended New Law is no other than the Old Law furbiſhed up again, that in it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf it muſt be eſſentially t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame, the Works and Juſtification by them, that if there be ſome little difference i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odalities it makes no eſſential Change, than is in a Man that wears one coloured Suit of Cloaths one day, and another on another Day. I argue, That Covenant that beſtows the Grace of the Promiſe without a previous Condition, is not a new Law; but the Covenant of Grace beſtows the Grace of it without previous Conditions performed by us. Therefore it beſtows eternal Life unconditionally; <hi>ergo,</hi> for it beſtows the firſt Grace (according to yours) unconditionally, which is Eternal Life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. If there be no need of a New Law, God is ſo wiſe he will not make a New Law, if there be no need of it or uſe for it, then the Goſpel is no New Law: But there's no need or uſe of a New Law.</p>
               <p>Minor, There's no need or uſe for it, neither in reſpect of Law or Goſpel Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Juſtice or of Grace. 1. There is no need or uſe in reſpect of Law or Juſtice, becauſe the old Law is a ſufficient Rule for diſtributive and commutative Juſtice, it condemns every Tranſgreſſion and Diſobedience eternally, it hath provided Curſe and Condemnation enough for the greateſt and moſt aggravated Sin, for unbelief in the leaſt and higheſt degree; and ſo for Impenitency: All the World is guilty by this Law, God rules the World by it, and will judge it by it, there's not the leaſt or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Duty but is here commanded, which is or ſhall be the Will of God, not only in way of moral Duty, but in all Matters of inſtituted Worſhip under the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Laſtly, in reſpect of Juſtification and Reward, if God had intended to have given Life as a Reward of the Works of any Law, he could as eaſily have done it by the Old Law, and ſure would never have made a new one to have done it by. 2. There is no need of a new Law in regard of the Diſpenſation of the Grace of the Goſpel: Becauſe what the Goſpel doth its in way of delivery of Man from the Curſe of the Law that they lye already under; and here there is no need of Law, becauſe its done all in a way of free Grace, Pardon of a condemned Priſoner muſt come meerly from the good will of the Prince, its inconſiſtent with his Prerogative to be bound to it by a Law; therefore God reſerves this Prerogative, he will have Mercy on whom he will have Mercy. And its needleſs in reſpect of the condemned p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſon, becauſe there's need of nothing but a free Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of Grace and Mercy to a condemned Priſoner, if he refuſes it its at his own peril, its his chooſing; but to remain <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> under the Law, that he was condemned by, and to be executed according to it. You'll ſay, there's need of a new Law in reſpect of new Obedience. <hi>A.</hi> I ſay no; for God's Law is ſtill perfect in reſpect of the Rule of Obedience. 2. The Goſpel requires no other Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience materially than what the Law required. 3. The Goſpel makes proviſion in the diſpenſation of free Grace for all Obedience the Law requires, for the perfection of it in Chriſt, for our Conformity to it through its Promiſe, teaching and new creating, and writing that Law anew in our Hearts which the Fall had blotted out. Well, to conclude this Argument, the Apoſtle expreſsly ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Now without Law,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God is made manifeſt, being witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets, i. e.</hi> by the whole Old Teſtament, as the Jews were wont to divide it; and therefore ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. for Diſtinction from Law, in the Senſe that he took it in, when he ſaith, without Law: new Obedience is obedience to the Law, from a new Life, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inciples, Strength, and for new Ends.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. That which is inconſiſtent with the Grace of God in the Goſpel, is not to be admitted; but that the Goſpel ſhould be a Law with Sanction, is inconſiſtent with the Grace of God in the Goſpel. <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Minor is eaſily made manifeſt, 1. From
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95981:22"/> the Nature of a Law, that's to enforce's Obedience; where a thing is freely given, its expected it ſhould be freely received and not enforced. 2. Its inconſiſtent with ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mercy to poor, lame, blind Cripples, to offer them Relief upon unperformable Conditions. Yea, its alſo an abuſe of Juſtice to make a Law, That lame Men ſhould walk before their Limbs be reſtored: I pray did Chriſt heal the Diſeaſed, reſtore the Lunaticks, raiſe the Dead, caſt out Devils, by a Law? 3. If it be conſiſtent with the Grace of the Goſpel to act by a Law in ſaving Sinners, it muſt be before Regeneration or after; not before, for then they will come under no Law, they are out in Rebellion againſt all Law, nay they are already in the Cuſtody of the Law, and therefore not capable of coming under the Terms of another. 2. Their Salvation muſt lye in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of them from the Cuſtody and Curſe of that they are under; which cannot be by making Terms with them, but with the Law offended that detains them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be mere Grace without a Law, that muſt open the Priſon Doors to them. 3. You ſay the firſt Grace is abſolutely and freely given, therefore the Sinner can come under no terms of Law in order to the bringing him into a ſtate of Grace, for terms of a Law laid upon any ſuppoſeth a Power and Ability in them to perform the ſaid terms, if they will, and that they can both will and do if they will. It is not a new Law after Regeneracy, for then Grace begun would ceaſe to be free Grace after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Chriſt is not only the Author, but the Finiſher of our Faith and Obedience, our perſeverance and ſtanding in Grace would not be ſo ſecure as its beginning, the Grace of the Covenant would not be homogeneous, one part would be free and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her conditional and upon Terms; but the Operation of the Spirit and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of after-grace, they are all of the ſame nature from firſt to laſt, as God begins ſo he perfects and compleats the new Man; he works all our Works in us, all-a-long, in the ſame way and manner as they are begun.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. If the Goſpel be a new Law, it was made as ſoon as the old Law was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: And, as new as it is, it muſt be that Law by which the Patriarchs antidiluvian and poſtdiluvians were ſaved. This conſequence, I ſuppoſe, cannot be denied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſaved even as they, and the Goſpel was preached unto them. But there was no ſuch new Law from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi>'s time: 1. The Goſpel was not delivered to our firſt Parents in the terms of a Law, but abſolutely ſo to <hi>Abraham.</hi> The Apoſtle is moſt expreſs in it, That there was no Law given to his time, that could be a Goſpel, <hi>i. e.</hi> that could give Life to Sinners, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. <hi>If there had a Law been given which could have given life, verily Righteouſneſs had been by a Law:</hi> And now I pray except not at my reading <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Law, indefinitely underſtanding any Law, for our Tranſlators render it ſo; and I muſt tell you they ſhould by the ſame reaſon have rendred <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſame manner, and then the Text had been uniform in the Tranſlation as in the Original, <hi>if there had been a Law (any Law) given, which could have given Life, verily Righteouſneſs had been by a Law:</hi> Therefore your new Law was not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven before <hi>Paul</hi>'s Time, but the Goſpel was, therefore the Goſpel is no Law with Sanction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> on this place ſaith thus. <q>Though thoſe Words of <hi>Paul</hi> be never ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain, yet the Papiſts have this wicked Gloſs always ready, That he ſpeaketh only of the Ceremonial Law: But <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh plainly, and excepteth no Law, whether Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or Ceremonial, or <hi>any other:</hi> Wherefore their Gloſs is not worth a Ruſh. And contrariwiſe we affirm, That there is <hi>no Law, whether Man's Law or God's Law</hi> that giveth Life; therefore we put as great a difference between the Law and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as between Life and Death, between Heaven and Hell; and the Cauſe that moveth us ſo to affirm, is, That the Apoſtle ſaith, The Law is not given to juſtifie, to give Life and to ſave, but only to kill and to deſtroy, contrary to the Opinion of all Men naturally, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Difference of the Offices of the Law and the Goſpel keepeth all Chriſtian Doctrin in its true and proper uſe.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95981:22"/>
               <p>This Witneſs of <hi>Luther</hi> I can ſet againſt all the Teſtimonies you bring from any what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, who hold or have held the Goſpel a Law with Sanction, as you do; divers may ſpeak of it under the term of a Law of Faith, or underſtanding by Law the Precepts of the Goſpel; but if they plead, that the true and proper nature of the Goſpel is a Law with Sanction, as you do, I do renounce their Opinion, and do oppoſe them therein, as I do you, it being as ſuch fundamentally deſtructive to the Goſpel, and the whole nature of the Grace of it.</p>
               <p>And on <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. — <q>Chriſt being made under the Law, is not a Law-giver, or a Judge after the Law, but in that he made himſelf ſubject to the Law, he delivered us from the Curſe thereof. Now whereas Chriſt under the Goſpel giveth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and teacheth the Law, or expoundeth it rather, this pertaineth not to the Doctrin of Juſtification, but of good Works. Moreover, It is not the proper Office of Chriſt (for which he came into the World) to teach the Law, but acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, as it was to heal the weak, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — Wherefore the true proper Office of Chriſt is to wreſtle with the Law, — to conquer and aboliſh Sin and Death, — to deliver the faithful from the Law and all Evils — Let us learn to put a difference between Chriſt and a Law-giver, — that when the Devil goes about to trouble us under his Name, we may know him to be a very Fiend. — Chriſt is no <hi>Moſes,</hi> he is nothing elſe but Infinite Mercy, freely giving. On <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Now as it is the greateſt knowledge and cunning that Chriſtians have thus to define Chriſt, ſo of all things it is hardeſt. I my ſelf in this great light of the Goſpel, wherein I have been ſo long exerciſed, to hold the diſtinction of Chriſt which <hi>Paul</hi> giveth ſo deeply, hath the Doctrin and peſtilent Opinion, that Chriſt is a Law-giver, entred into my Bones. You young Men therefore are in a far happier condition, for you are not inſected with thoſe pernicious Errours wherein I have been ſo muzled and drowned from my youth, that at my hearing the Name of Chriſt, my Heart hath trembled and quaked for fear, for I was perſwaded, that he was a ſevere Judge; wherefore it is to me a double trouble to correct and reform this Evil: 1. To forget, cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mn and reſiſt this old-grounded Errour, That Chriſt is a Law-giver and a Judge. 2. To plant in my Heart a new and true perſwaſion of Chriſt, that he is a Juſtifier and a Saviour. Ye that are young may learn with much leſs difficulty to know Chriſt purely and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, if you will.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 8. If the Goſpel be a new Law, then we muſt have a double Righteouſneſs for our juſtification; but we have not a double Righteouſneſs for our juſtification, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the conſequence is good, 1. From moſt of your Conceſſions, that we have the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and that which you call ſubordinate. [You ſhould rather have ſaid as Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> argues, that Chriſt's righteouſneſs is the ſubordinate, it being <hi>in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad,</hi> in order to our juſtification by a new Law.] Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and others ſpeak more diſtinctly and ſay, a legal and evangelical righteouſneſs; but, in truth, it muſt be two legal righteouſneſſes: For, 2. There's no Law but muſt have a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>culiar diſtinct righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs from that of any other Law, whereby a Man under it muſt be juſtified, and all the righteouſneſs that ſerves for juſtification by another Law, hath nothing to do in our juſtification by the ſaid Law; and therefore there muſt be two diſtinct Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and two diſtinct Juſtifications, as there are two diſtinct Laws. Unleſs you ſay the old Law is vacated, which is a contradiction; if you do but own, that Chriſt is the end of that Law for righteouſneſs to every one that be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieved, and then it cannot be vacated, for a Law vacated and a Law in force is a contradiction, and a Law fulfilled to every jot and tittle to every believer remains in force. Therefore it remains, that we have two righteouſneſſes for juſtification, and both legal, becauſe all Law-righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is legal; Chriſt's ſingle righteouſneſs is indeed legal in reſpect of the Law, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vangelical in reſpect of ſinners, it being to them the gift of righteouſneſs; ſo with us the ſame thing differs only reſpectively. 3. There muſt be as diſtinct righteouſneſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95981:23"/> for juſtification, as there is unrighteouſneſs for condemnation; but each Law hath its diſtinct unrighteouſneſs for condemnation.</p>
               <p>The Minor is eaſily proved, that we have not two righteouſneſſes for juſtification, for if we have, 1. Chriſt's righteouſneſs is not enough for our juſtification unto life, contrary to the Scripture. 2. All the Popiſh Doctrin will unavoidably come in at this gate, which is wide enough for it. 3. Our own Works, call them what you will, let them be Faith and ſincere Obedience, imperfect Holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt come in for a ſhare in our juſtification, contrary to <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.4, 5. and an hundred places of Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, nay, for the whole of our juſtification by the new Law; for the righteouſneſs that anſwers that, muſt be diſtinct from the righteouſneſs that anſwers the old Law; to enervate this Doctrin, many have wrote to very good purpoſe, in particular that moſt worthy Divine, Mr. <hi>Traughton</hi> in his <hi>Lutherus redivivus,</hi> a Book worth every Chriſtian's having.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>Hath the Goſpel-Covenant no Sanction? what think you of</hi> Heb. 8.6?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> You might have ſaid <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15, 16. I ſaid not, that the Goſpel-Covenant hath no Sanction: it hath a Sanction, as a Teſtament in the Death of Chriſt, in which the Law is ſatisfied for us, and upon which the better, abſolute and clear Promiſes are founded; and herein was that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> placed, the eſtabliſhment of the Promiſes of Life and Salvation, on the ſure Conditions of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and not of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>What will become of Dr.</hi> Owen<hi>'s Law of Juſtification,</hi> p. 167.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> His Law of Juſtification is the Law that Chriſt came under, in doing and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the fulfilling God's Will for the juſtification of a ſinner; this was the Law that was in his heart; for the Doctor's words are, Not that he did as a King conſtitute the the Law of Juſtification, (as you ſay) for it was given and eſtabliſhed in the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and he came to put it in execution.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>It's one thing to be juſtified for Faith, and another to be juſtified by it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>R.</label> I ſay ſo too, if it be in the Apoſtle's ſenſe, <hi>by Faith</hi> be in oppoſition to <hi>by Works;</hi> but if you make Faith a Law-condition, then this <hi>by</hi> becomes <hi>for,</hi> and it ſignifies juſt as much as being juſtified by Works. And thus Mr. <hi>Bulkly</hi> in your own Quotation is againſt you, for he ſaith, <hi>If we make the Commandment of Believing to be legal, then the Promiſe of Life, upon the Condition of Believing, muſt be legal alſo.</hi> And ſo it muſt needs be upon your Hypotheſis, that the Goſpel is a Law. You often ſay, the Goſpel-Law is not a Law of Works, and that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith ſo, <hi>p.</hi> 26. What is ſo ſaid either by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle or you, the Goſpel is denied thereby to be a Law with Sanction or Law-Covenant, for if there be no Works as Condition of it, there's nothing but Promiſe; but where is your ſincere, conditional, imperfect Obedience, if there be no Works? It's abſurd to ſay the firſt Grace is a Condition required of us, becauſe you grant it abſolute.</p>
               <p>You tell us what Dr. <hi>O.</hi> ſaith on <hi>Pſ.</hi> 130 <hi>p.</hi> 230. <hi>This is the inviolable Law of the Goſpel; i. e.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and forgiveneſs are inſeparably conjoyned, which hath nothing of your ſenſe in it. Concerning Faith's being the Condition of a Law with Sanction, he ſaith nothing; he means no more but that they are connexed by God's conſtitution. So there are many things connexed in the Promiſe, as Faith and Forgiveneſs, Faith and Repentance, Faith and Love, Juſtification and Sanctification and Glorification. I could quote you a hundred places out of Dr. <hi>O.</hi> where he militates againſt this very Principle of yours: See Dr. <hi>O.</hi> of Juſtifie. <hi>p.</hi> 407. <q>The Apoſtle ſpeaks not one word of the Excluſion of the Merit of Works, only he excludes all Works whatſoever. — Some think they are injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly dealt withal, when they are charged with maintaining Merit— Yet thoſe that beſt underſtand themſelves and the Controverſie, are not ſo averſe to any kind of merits, knowing that it's inſeparable from Works.— Thoſe among us who plead for Works in our Juſtification, as they uſe many diſtinctions to explain their minds and free themſelves from a co-incidence with that of the Papiſts, they deny the name of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95981:23"/> Merit in the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo do the Socinians.</q> See more, <hi>p.</hi> 408, 409. where he ſhews all Works before and after Grace are excluded.</p>
               <p>What you quote out of my honoured Father's Book, I ſee nothing contradicts me, if rightly underſtood; had not your Doctrin been contrary to his, (tho' I hope I ſhould defend the truth, according to my light and conſcience, tho' againſt my own Father) I ſhould never have given you the leaſt oppoſition; but it's not Human Authority muſt turn the Scales in theſe Matters. You quote Mens tranſient Expreſſions that ſpeak of a Goſpel-law and Conditions in a ſenſe that may be born with, when they approve themſelves clear in all main Points: others ſpeaking in ſuch a Dialect in Sermons and Practical Diſcourſes; To ſhew that ſuch things as God hath conjoyned, Man is not to ſever. As for the two great Divines, beſides D. <hi>O.</hi> I mean Dr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clarkſon,</hi> I know them to be expreſly againſt your Notion of the conditionality of the Covenant, and by what you quote out of them, it appears to be ſo. See Dr. <hi>Goodwin</hi>'s Judgment about Condition, Whether Faith be a Condition, Sermon XXII. <hi>p.</hi> 301. <q>I would have this word laid aſide, I ſee both Parties ſpeak faintly on't; <hi>Perkins</hi> on the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and another. — There is danger in the uſe of it, a Condition may be pleaded. 2. In thoſe Expreſſions, if a Man believeth he ſhall be ſaved, import, that he that doth ſo, ſhall be ſaved in the event, which the Elect only are, to whom he giveth Faith. — My Beloved, the nature of Faith is modeſt, it never maketh plea for it ſelf; if it were a Condition, a Man might plead it before God; and the making it a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſeems to me, to import as if there were an univerſal Grace; and that it is the Condition terminateh it to this Man and not to that. What Mr. <hi>Clerkſon</hi> ſaith, is nothing to your purpoſe; for he ſaith, The firſt Bleſſings of the Covenant are promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed abſolutely, and ſubſequent Bleſſings, are in ſome ſenſe Conditional.— Not that God makes a conditional Bargain with us, but becauſe divine Wiſdom hath made a connexion between theſe Bleſſings that they ſhall never be ſeparated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Laſtly, I ſhall give an Account of the beginning and progreſs of this Neonomian Error.</head>
               <p>This Doctrin was firſt forged by the Phariſees of old, who did not believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves juſtified by perfect Obedience to the moral Law, their owning the Sacrifices and other Types (their Goſpel) being a ſufficient evidence that they acknowledged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great Sinners, and far enough from perfect Obedience; they only thought that Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that they did perform, was through the merciful Nature of God accepted to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of Life, and their Sins expiated by Sacrifices.</p>
               <p>For not only the Scriptures give us full aſſurance of this to be truth, but it were eaſy to ſhew what the Opinion of the ancient and latter Jews were, in this Matter. 1. They placed their Righteouſneſs, not in perfect Obedience, but in ſincere. So <hi>Paul,</hi> before his Converſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.5.9. Chap. 23. 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9. The Jews went to eſtabliſh their own Righteouſneſs and their imperfect Obedience, as ſuch, in conjunction with the attoning Sacrifices for their Juſtification. And <hi>R. Menahem</hi> ſaith, <hi>Scito vitam Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis in praeceptis;</hi> Know that the Life of Man, in the Precepts, is according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that he hath in doing them; But they ſay, Faith is the cauſe of Bleſſedneſs, and, therefore, the cauſe of eternal Life. Thus the Author of <hi>Sepher Ikkarim.</hi> And that Faith juſtifies as Righteouſneſs itſelf; for, ſaith the ſame Author, Our Father <hi>Abraham</hi> was praiſed, by reaſon of his Faith; for it's ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. <hi>He believed God, and it was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> And that this Doctrin was that which <hi>Paul</hi> contendeth with the judaizing Chriſtians about, and the falſe Teachers among them, I doubt not in the leaſt, and am very apt to believe, that it was theſe Neonomians that laid that Charge upon <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrin; that it was a Doctrin of Licentiouſneſs, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95981:24"/> made ſo great a Cry againſt it, for Antinomianiſm; or as being deſtructive to the Righteouſneſs of the Law and Obedience thereunto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip,</hi> a Presbyter and Hearer of <hi>Hierom,</hi> on <hi>Job</hi> 42. tells of a Heretick, then liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that held this Opinion, That the Goſpel was a Law, <hi>Chriſtop. Pelarg.</hi> The next I find it charged upon, is <hi>Pelagius,</hi> as one of h s grand Hereſies. And from the Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſaith Dr. <hi>Leydecker,</hi> the Papiſts have taken up this Principle. <hi>The Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>Anath.</hi> 20. <q>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe all that ſay the Goſpel is a Promiſe without condition of obſerving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. <hi>And</hi> Anath. <hi>21.</hi> They Curſe thoſe that ſay, Chriſt is given for a Redeemer, and not a Law-maker. <hi>And</hi> Anath. <hi>26.</hi> They Curſe them that ſay, The juſt ought not to expect a Reward for their Works. <hi>Peter a Soto</hi> tells us, the Catholick Church doth hold, That Chriſt gave a new Law.</q> The ſame ſaith S. <hi>De Clara. It is generally h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld by all the Jeſuits.</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin <hi>in his</hi> Controv. de Juſtif. <hi>contends, That the Goſpel, as ſuch, is a Law; and that it contains proper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aws, with Threats and Promiſes, and requires Obedience as the Condition of Life, and of the accompliſhments of Promiſes, which are ſo conditionated; and that Merits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe defended, which the Papacy holds.</hi> Gregory de Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntia <hi>tells us, They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the uſual diſtinction of Law and Goſpel,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Law Promiſes are conditional, the Goſpel Promiſes free and abſolute.</hi> Tom. 2. Controv. Diſput. 7. Q 6. <hi>Le calls it a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> in Act. &amp; Mon. Impr. 7. p. 34. vol. 1. gives this following Account of the Papiſt's Opinion in this Point, <hi>They ſay,</hi> Moſes <hi>was a giver of the old Law, Chriſt of the new. Thus, imagine they, the Goſpel to be nothing elſe but a new Law, given by Chriſt, binding to the Promiſes the Conditions of our doings and deſervings, no otherwiſe than to the old Law; and ſo divide they the whole Law into three parts, the Law of Nature, the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and the Law of Chriſt, to the fulfilling whereof they attribute Juſtification. And thus they lead the Conſciences of Men in doubt, and induce many Errors, bringing the People into a falſe opinion of Chriſt, as tho' he were not a Remedy againſt the Law, but came as another</hi> Moſes <hi>to give a new Law to the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Barns,</hi> who ſuffered Martyrdom in <hi>Henry</hi> VIII.'s time, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1541. vigour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly oppoſed the Popiſh Biſhops in this Point; as appears by his excellent Treatiſe of Juſtification.</p>
               <p>In defending Juſtification, by Faith alone, according to the true meaning of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> hath theſe Paſſages.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It were but loſt labour for <hi>Paul</hi> to prove that Works did help to Juſtification; for that the Jews did grant, and required no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re; but that which they ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was, that Works might not be clearly excluded. But here, peradventure, it will be ſaid, that <hi>Paul</hi> condemns the Works of the old Law, but not of the new Law; Are you now ſatisfied in your Conſciences? Think you, that you have now aſſoyled <hi>Paul</hi>'s Argument? Think you to be thus diſcharged before God? Go boldly to the Judgment of God, with this Evaſion, and doubt not but then you ſhall find St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiflly and ſtrongly againſt you, and your new Works, as ever he was againſt the Jews and their old Works. Briefly, what Works can you excogitate to do, which be not in the old Law, and of the old Law? Therefore he ſpeaks of all manner of Works; for the Law includeth all Works that ever God inſtituted, the higheſt, beſt and moſt of Perfection; what Works, in the new Law, have you better than thoſe of the old Law? <hi>&amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> — But grant that there be certain Works of the new Law which be not of the old; yet have you not, nor can prove that theſe ſhall juſtify; for there can be no more goodneſs in Works, than were in the Works of the old Law, for they were to Gods Honour, and the Profit of the Neighbour, and yet you grant they cannot juſtify. St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s againſt them that were Chriſtned, and had Works of the old Law and of the new; yet concludes, that Chriſt alone juſtified. Mark his Argument; If Righteouſneſs cometh by the Law, then is Chriſt dead in vain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he proceeds to enervate this Doctrin of Neomianiſm.</q>
               </p>
               <p>From the Papiſts the Socinians took up this Doctrin, as Dr. <hi>Leidaker</hi> ſhews, ſtyling them, Our new Pelagians. They do indeed (ſaith he) exclude Ceremonial Works,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95981:24"/> and Works of the Jews, who oppoſe the Goſpel, but when they may ſeem to differ from the Roman Catholicks in the Doctrin of Merit, they anſwer;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socin.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Paul</hi> treats concerning perfect Works of that Law, and ſeeing none can be juſtified by them, the Law requiring perfect Obedience; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We are juſtified by faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſo far as a man is able to perform them.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>Paul</hi> excludes Works of the Law not interrupted by Sin (<hi>i. e.</hi> perfect perſevering Works) or merits, not thoſe that are performed according to the mild Law of the Goſpel: And he takes notice how Dr. <hi>P. Barrow,</hi> a Divinity Profeſſor in <hi>England,</hi> was among the firſt of ours that deſerted the true Doctrin, and an aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of this Doctrin, That the Goſpel is a new Law, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that no Man was ever juſtified by a perfect obſervance of the Law, but by that Obſervation which depends upon Mercy, and includes pardon of Sin the regenerate do perform that Law; in his Treatiſe <hi>de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeſtantia legis, c.</hi> 13. This Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> the Arminians, when they began to ſpring up, highly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded, ſaith Dr. <hi>Leidaker;</hi> His Words are, <hi>Similes habent labra lactucas;</hi> He ſays, they changed the very Decalogue into a Covenant of Grace, confounding it with the Goſpel, aſſerting a Covenant of Works; ſaying, That notwithſtanding the giving Chriſt, God might have ſet up again a Covenant of Works, but he would not, becauſe of the weakneſs of the Fleſh: Therefore in the room of the rigid Covenant of Works he ſubſtituted a milder Covenant, mixed with goodneſs and grace, in which Faith with imperfect Obedience to the Law might be accepted for perfect Righteouſneſs unto Life. Theſe Doctrins Arminians began to vent, but <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> taught them openly, whom <hi>Curcellius</hi> alſo followed as his Maſter, and more lately Dr. <hi>Limburgius;</hi> who aſſerts, That the Scripture no where teacheth Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is imputed to us; and ſaith, This Error (ſo he calls the Doctrin of the imputation of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs) ariſeth from a falſe Opinion, That Chriſt gave full Satisfaction to vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juſtice for all the Sins of the Elect, and bore their Puniſhment in their ſtead, and fulfilled the Law for them: That the Goſpel contains no Precepts, but in reſpect of the Elect are meer Promiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Doctrin of <hi>Limbergius</hi> are (ſaith the ſaid learned Author) <hi>tantum non Sociniana:</hi> He ſheweth how this Man excludes all Works from Juſtification, but only the Works of the new Law. He ſhews how the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants, the Dutch Arminians took up with this Doctrin; how it prevailed in <hi>France,</hi> which after the endeavours of <hi>Meliterius</hi> and <hi>Corducus, Camero</hi>'s <hi>triplex foedus,</hi> gave the greateſt occaſion to, which <hi>Cocceius</hi> and his followers oppoſed: And laſtly ſhews how it hath prevailed in <hi>England,</hi> in oppoſition to which the Labours of Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> in his Treatiſe of Juſtification, and of Mr. <hi>Troughton,</hi> in his <hi>Lutherus redivivus,</hi> is highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by him.</p>
               <p>From all which it doth appear, That this is no new Error, but an old ones ever ſince Chriſt's and the Apoſtles times, and hath been a leading Principle to all Doctrins, contrary to the free Juſtification of a Sinner by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt alone, apprehended by Faith: And the foundation of the Doctrin of Free-will, and the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Power and Ability of fallen Man, to do good Works that are pleaſing unto God, and in ſome way or other, in part or in whole, rewardable.</p>
               <p>He that will ſee a full account of this Doctrin, from tho Poſitions of the Jeſuites, and a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear Refutation thereof, and all their Arguments they bring for it, even more than you do, let him read, the learned Dr. <hi>Chriſtopher Pelargus, loco</hi> xii. <hi>de Evangelio,</hi> in his <hi>Jeſuitiſmus,</hi> printed <hi>Ann. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 1608.</p>
               <p>Divers Paſſages in your Reply and its Preface, wherein you lie open, I have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted remarking upon: 1. For brevity ſake. 2. Such as concern others, I leave to them. 3. As to all material Points, in difference, you'l ſee my mind elſewhere. I ſhall only note, how weak and abſurd the Reaſon is, you give, for your deſiring the Teſtimony of ſo many to your Book, <hi>viz. Becauſe the People do often value Names more than Arguments.</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:95981:25"/> Q. D. The People muſt be lead by an Implicit Faith, as in days paſt; <hi>Populus vult decipi, ergo decipiatur.</hi> Can Proteſtants think this Reaſon is for their Honour and Safety? But I ſpare you; and do aſſure you, my Deſign hath not been for Contention, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for what I have thought to be the Truth; but my cordial Deſire is, that all may iſſue in the Unity of the Spirit of Truth and Peace, and what collateral Expreſſions have fallen from my Pen, from firſt to laſt, that are juſtly diſreliſhed by you, or any other that feareth the Lord, aſcribe it to human Frailty, which I am lyable to; and uſually may be ſeen in Conteſts of this Nature, how juſt ſoever they be. Excuſe my plainneſs of Speech throughout, and allow ſomething to every Man's natural Temper and Diſpoſition. Sir, I am willing to be, notwithſtanding all that hath paſſed,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your faithful Friend and Brother in the Lord, <hi>J. C.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Henry Barnard,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>EXamen Confectionis Pacificae:</hi> Or, a friendly Examination of the Pacifick Paper; chiefly concerning the conſiſtency of Abſolute Election of particular Perſons with the Univerſality of Redemption, and the Conditionality of the Covenant of Grace: Wherein alſo the New Scheme is clearly declared. By <hi>Iſaac Chancy,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The old Man's Legacy to his Daughters: Wherein the hidden Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Faith and Experience are briefly diſcuſſed and laid down, in a plain and familiar Dialogue; in ſix ſeveral Conferences betwix the Author's two Daughters, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Margaret.</hi> To which is added, Some Choice Diſcoveries of the Author's moſt excellent Experiences; in two Parts. Written by <hi>N. T.</hi> deceaſed, when near Ninety Years of Age, for the private Uſe of his Daughters aforeſaid; and now made publick, at the requeſt of many, by an Admirer of Grace and Truth.</p>
            <p>The Banquetting-houſe, or, a Feaſt of Fat Things: A Divine Poem, opening many Sacred Scripture Myſteries, profitable for all who would attain to the Saving Knowledg of God and of Jeſus Chriſt. Written by <hi>Benjamin Keach,</hi> Author of <hi>War with the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chirurgus Marinus:</hi> Or, the Sea-Chirurgion; being Inſtructions to Junior Chirurgick Practitioners, who deſign to ſerve at Sea in this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy. In two general Parts: The firſt Part contains neceſſary Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, how the Chirurgion ſhould furniſh himſelf with Medicines, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Neceſſaries fit for that Office; together with a Medicinal Catalogue, and an exemplary Invoyce. The ſecond Part contains the Chirurgions Practice at Sea, both Chirurgical and Phyſical; which practical Part ſerves as well at Land as at Sea. By <hi>John Moyle, Sen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt part of Neonomianiſm Unmask'd, in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Dan. VVilliams</hi>'s firſt Book: Is now in the Preſs, and in a few Days will be publiſhed.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
